解散監管機構並非我們的初衷
We have no intention of dismantling the regulatory agencies.
但實際上 我們整天被這些低效繁瑣的規則所糾纏
However, we must come to grips with inefficient and burdensome regulations.
我們要裁撤那些毫無效益非必要的部門
We will eliminate those that are unproductive and unnecessary.
取消那些過時的規章制度 授予銀行全新的職權
Tearing down these antiquated walls and granting banks significant new authority.
銀行業迎來利好消息
In a victory for the banking industry,
國會通過了立法
Congress has approved legislation
准許商業銀行和投資銀行進行合併
which will allow commercial and investment banks
形成史上最大的 業務覆蓋全球的金融機構
to merge and form institutions of unprecedented size and global reach.
大而不倒
我認為我們沒有必要為了防範管制風險而去增加管制
I think it's very important for us not to introduce regulation for regulation's sake.
我一直堅信著美國夢
I do believe in the American dream.
而擁有自己的房產則是夢開始的地方
Owning a home is a part of that dream.
--==聖城家園SCG字幕組 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
僅供翻譯交流使用, 禁止用於商業用途
我們正採取措施 幫助數以萬計的美國人擁有自己的房產
We are taking action to bring many thousands of Americans closer to owning a home.
這項計劃不僅有利於全體公民
This project not only is good for the soul of the country,
同時也能帶動國家經濟的發展
it's good for the pocketbook of the country as well.
房地產市場已經近乎瘋狂
The housing market has reached frantic proportions.
大家似乎都在忙著蓋房子 然後進行買賣
It seems that everybody is building, buying or selling.
道瓊斯和標普指數雙雙創出新高
The Dow and the S&P both breaking records.
高盛集團今年的利潤飆升93%
Profits soared 93% at Goldman Sachs this year.
交易員中的佼佼者和銀行從業人員收入預計將達到1000萬
Hotshot traders and bankers can expect to take home 10, 25,
2500萬 甚至是5000萬
and in some cases, $50 million.
這一切好得近乎天方夜譚了
Things that are too good to be true, are.
當你看到其中的...
When you see something coming...
房地產業的泡沫...
The real estate bubble...
- 房地產泡沫  - 泡沫
- Housing bubble.  - Bubble.
切不可視而不見
don't put it off.
要立即採取行動
Take action immediately.
泡沫會逐漸緩解 還是只能等到破滅?
Will there be a soft landing, or will the bubble burst?
--==聖城家園SCG字幕組 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
協調：瀟妹紙
翻譯：Flower一休 千欲 藍岸 wendychen11 13711 Kim
校對：微微
最新消息 次貸市場開始分崩離析
The new story, the mortgage meltdown.
由於次貸危機的發生 今天上午的最新數字表明
This morning in the mortgage meltdown, new numbers showing
失去住所的美國人數又創新高
that a record number of Americans are losing their homes.
在過去幾個月的時間 美國有70多家從事次貸業務的公司紛紛倒閉
More than 70 mortgage companies have failed in the last few months in America,
而現在貝爾斯登 以及大銀行等大型企業
and now the biggest of the big companies, the Bear Stearns, the big banks,
要開始承擔這一後果了
are caught holding the bag.
貝爾斯登 這家國內排名第五的投資銀行
The fifth largest investment bank in the country, Bear Stearns,
以每股2美金的股價出售給了摩根大通銀行
is being sold for just $2 a share to JPMorgan.
這宗交易是在政府的協助下進行的 目的是為了保全
It's being assisted by the government, which is stepping in to guarantee
貝爾斯登帳下的300億美金的不良房地產資產
some $30 billion in Bear's toxic real estate assets.
你一定能想像得出來 Hank Paulson被布什總統任命為財政部長的時候
You've got to imagine that Hank Paulson didn't think he signed up for this
不會想到有一天會去簽署這樣一份文件
when President Bush picked him to become Treasury Secretary.
現在Hank Paulson可能不得不取消一些撤銷管制的規定
Hank Paulson may now have to undo some of the deregulation measures
而這些措施恰恰是在他主管高盛集團時與華爾街上的同行們一直努力倡導的
that he and his peers on Wall Street pushed through when he ran Goldman.
Hank Paulson財長今天上午對Matt Lauer說
Treasury Secretary Hank Paulson telling Matt Lauer this morning,
"我們已經克服了一切困難 我對我們的市場充滿信心
"We're all over it. I've got great confidence in our markets.
它們是富有彈性和可塑性的"
They're resilient. They're flexible."
Ali 事實上貝爾斯登的收購事件只是掀開了冰山一角
Ali, the truth is that Bear Stearns is only a very small fraction of this story.
我們的經濟很可能會大幅衰退
Our economy could face far worse than a recession.
受貝爾斯登倒閉的影響 雷曼兄弟忙於
In the wake of Bear's collapse, Lehman Brothers is scrambling
說服投資者相信 次貸危機不會對雷曼兄弟的資產造成太大影響
to reassure investors about the impact of the mortgage crisis on its own assets.
今天上午雷曼兄弟的保證人遭受了一系列的壓力
Insurers of the firm under a great deal of pressure this morning.
Dick Fuld 在雷曼工作了39年
Dick Fuld, a 39-year veteran of Lehman
並且是華爾街上大型投資銀行中任職最久的首席執行官
and the longest-running CEO of a major investment bank on Wall Street,
曾多次讓公司在危機中起死回生
has pulled the firm back from the brink during other crises,
Richard Fuld 雷曼兄弟主席兼首席執行官
但是今天 我第一次聽到了投資者們對他的領導能力的質疑聲
but today, for the first time that I'm hearing it, investors are questioning his leadership.
- 混蛋  - 投資者們
- Motherfucker.  - One key question
對雷曼兄弟最關注的一個問題就是
investors have for Lehman Brothers,
"這家投資銀行的盈利能力到底如何?"
"What's the true earnings power of this investment bank's business?"
Joe Gregory 雷曼兄弟總裁兼首席運營官
- 嘿  - 趕緊到我這兒來
- Hey.  - Get up here.
我們得去搬救兵了
We gotta start stacking sand bags.
你在說什麼啊?
What are you talking about?
我們的股價暴跌了21% 從市價上看 我個人就損失了9000萬
We're down 21%. On paper, I just lost $90 million, personally.
隨著投資者不斷拋售雷曼兄弟的股票
With investors pummeling Lehman shares,
今天上午最大的一個疑問就是
the big question this morning is,
"Fuld還有何退路?"
"What options does Fuld have?"
截至目前 他還沒能夠籌措到新的投資
So far, he has failed to raise new capital
而事實上他的競爭對手們已經拿到了
while virtually all of his rivals have already done so.
財政部長 高盛前董事會主席兼首席執行官
現在 對沖基金經理David Einhorn已經在公開質疑公佈數字的準確性了
And now, hedge fund manager David Einhorn is publicly questioning the accuracy of the fund numbers
有什麼好消息嗎?
Anything good?
這是一隻紅尾鷹 今年頭回看到
It's a red-tailed hawk, first one this year.
Dick Fuld在1號線上等著
Dick Fuld's on one.
提供可信的答案
to provide credible answers.
讓我們來一起分析一下這些 呃
So let's go through a couple of those, uh,
被你稱為差異的東西 因為...
what you call discrepancies, because...
- 上午的日子不好過吧?  - 我們有高收益
- Tough morning?  - We show top-quality earnings,
- 粉碎了所有之前的預測  - 沒錯
- we beat every prediction.  - Yeah.
這是做空者的行為 你也知道他們的一貫伎倆 先做空 然後彎曲事實
It's the damn short-sellers. You know the game, short and distort.
他們善於散佈謠言 然後從中大賺一筆
They're rumormongers and they're making a killing.
你對於籌集資金有什麼計劃?
What are your plans for a capital raise?
我們想的比你更遠 讓我把話再講得明白些
We're way ahead of you. Now, let me be clear,
我們不需要現金
we don't need the cash.
這是一種直覺
You know, it's about perception.
快說巴菲特
Buffett, Buffett.
我們正在考慮同沃倫·巴菲特進行接洽
We're thinking of reaching out to Warren Buffett.
很好
Great.
你和巴菲特有過交情 對吧?
You and Buffett go back, right?
幫幫我 給他打個電話
Do me a favor and call him.
告訴他雷曼兄弟有著很堅實的基礎
Tell him Lehman is rock solid.
作為財政部長 我不能鼓動他去進行某一項的投資
As Treasury Secretary, I can't advocate for a specific investment.
Erin Callan 雷曼兄弟首席財務官
Hank 你想不想讓我籌集到資金?
Hank, you want me to raise capital or not?
2008年5月24日 星期六
雷曼兄弟的規模要比貝爾斯登大得多
Lehman Brothers is a hell of a lot bigger than Bear Stearns.
市場開始恐慌了
The market is terrified.
我在高盛集團主政期間 從來沒有想過要去
When I was running Goldman, I never even conceived
請求財長為我促成一筆交易
of asking the Treasury Secretary to cut a deal for me.
沒錯 但是對貝爾斯登的緊急援助造成了...
Yeah, but the Bear bailout created...
不要把它說成是緊急援助
Please don't call it a bailout.
好吧 對貝爾斯登的一攬子大規模收購援助政策
Okay, the very large Bear Stearns purchase assistance package
使公眾產生了一種預期
created an expectation.
Fuld正期待您的直接介入
Fuld's counting on direct intervention from you.
巴菲特可以輕而易舉地解決這個問題
Buffett's a simple solution.
Jim Wilkinson 財政部參謀長
我覺得您應該去給他打這個電話
I think you make the call.
以什麼身份呢? 他的朋友? 以前為他提供服務的人? 還是以財長的身份?
As what? Warren's friend? His former banker? The Treasury Secretary?
不 還是讓Fuld自己去打給他吧
No. Fuld's calling him.
希望他能介入進來 這樣大家都能安心了
Hopefully he'll jump in and we can all relax.
安心? 我們剛剛處理了一家投資銀行 這會兒又有另一家在茍延殘喘
Relax? We just buried one investment bank, we got another one that's barely breathing.
這是一場關乎信心的博弈 如果人們對雷曼兄弟失去了信心
This is a confidence game. People lose faith in Lehman,
那後面的銀行就會像多米諾骨牌一樣成片地倒下
these banks are gonna drop like dominoes,
而我也無法為此再做出什麼了
and I don't have the authority to do a thing about it.
已經晚了 一切都已經太晚了
We're late. We've been late on everything.
Neel Kashkari 部長助理 處理國際事務
Neel的團隊正在研究這樣災難即將帶來的後果
Neel's team is working on some kind of a disaster scenario.
我們把它稱為"破杯"計劃
We're calling it the "Break the Glass" plan,
當您走投無路的時候就可以要求國會執行這項計劃
what to ask Congress for if your back's against the wall.
錢唄
Money.
就是向他們要錢唄
Is what you ask them for.
Michele Davis 部長助理 處理公共事務
問題在於 除非我們已經撞上了冰山 否則國會不會採取舉措
The problem is, Congress won't move until we've already hit the iceberg,
而到那時 一切都已經太晚了
and at that point, it may be too late.
你的意思是說 我掌管著美國財政部
So you're saying, with the full weight of the United States Treasury behind me,
而我能做的就是去找巴菲特求助?
all I can do is call Warren Buffett?
嗨 巴菲特 我是Hank
Hi, Warren. It's Hank.
我知道你和Dick Fuld已經談過了
I understand you've been talking to Dick Fuld.
華倫·巴菲特 世上最富有的人
Hank 你也知道我對那些投資銀行的擔憂
You know my misgivings, Hank, about investment banks.
他們一旦開始為自己進行交易時
As soon as they started trading for themselves,
那些風險經理就都失控了
the risk managers lost control.
我和所羅門兄弟公司有過一次不太愉快的合作經歷
I had a very unpleasant time with Salomon Brothers.
你說得有道理
That's fair enough.
但我們都知道投資銀行向來都是一個有利可圖的行業
But we both know that investment banking is a profitable business.
我猜它大概已經為你賺了數十億美金了吧?
I figure it made you a billion or so, huh?
我相信如果他們出價合理的話 你也不會袖手旁觀吧
I gotta believe that if the price was right, you wouldn't just walk away.
在事實面前才算數 你覺得呢?
You know a good deal when you see one. What say you?
還是你自己來判斷吧
I gotta leave that to your judgment.
大家的反應就好像我們是奸商一樣
People act like we're crack dealers.
沒人拿著槍去指向某人說
Nobody put a gun to anybody's head and said,
"嘿 獵人 買下這棟你償還不起的房子吧 等你住進去以後
"Hey, nimrod, buy a house you can't afford. And you know what? While you're at it,
再用它申請信用額度 這件就可以再買一艘船了"
put a line of credit on that baby and buy yourself a boat."
巴菲特給你回復了嗎?
You heard anything from Buffett?
他要求獲得股價為40美金的優先股 分紅為9%
He's asking for preferred shares at 40 with a dividend of 9%.
股價剛還在66塊呢 搞什麼鬼啊?
We were just at 66. What the fuck?
或許這只是遊戲的序幕吧 Dick
Maybe it's just an opening gambit, Dick.
聽上去更像是一種侮辱
Sounds more like a goddamn insult.
- 我來幫你弄吧 Dick  - 謝謝
- Let me get that, Dick.  - Thank you.
我們的股價已經跌到了36塊
We're at 36 right now.
這幾個月以來我們從未到過66快附近
We haven't been anywhere near 66 in months.
市場喜歡巴菲特
The markets like Buffett.
- 他的名字會在一夜之間推動股價上升  - 我才不在乎他是誰
- His name will push the price up overnight.  - I don't care who he is,
我不會用1年花費3億6000萬的代價去取悅他以謀求合作
I am not spending $360 million a year for the pleasure of doing business with him.
房地產市場會重新振作起來的
Real estate will come back.
韓國人有意介入
Koreans have been sniffing around.
這不好了 他們不會漫天要價
There you go. And they won't steal us blind.
這種場面以前我也經歷過 首席執行官們開始恐慌 然後廉價賣掉自己的股票
I've seen this before. CEOs panic and they sell out cheap.
現在 整條華爾街都認為已經到了火燒眉毛的時候
Right now, the Street's running around with its hair on fire,
但暴風雨總會過去的
but the storm always passes.
我們要充滿信心 然後 去參加高盛舉辦的午宴
We stand strong, and on the other side, we'll eat Goldman's lunch.
那我們該如何回復巴菲特呢?
So, what do we do about Buffett?
去他媽的巴菲特
Screw Warren Buffett.
每周早餐會議
- 他拒絕了?  - 雷曼兄弟的股價
- He passed?  - Lehman dropped
在今天上午已經跌到了28塊半 他到底是怎麼想的啊?
to 28 and a half this morning. What in the world is he thinking?
他根本沒有思考 他是在妄想 他認為巴菲特的開價太高了
He's not thinking. He's delusional. He thought the ask was too high.
Ben Bernanke 聯邦儲蓄主席
他得去籌措資金啊
He's gotta raise cash.
我也是這麼跟他說的
I told him that.
- 我找格林斯潘談過了  - 真的嗎?
- I spoke to Greenspan.  - Really?
他說住房市場供過於求 這就是問題所在
He says there's too much housing supply. That's the problem.
所以我們應該買下所有閒置房屋 不讓它們流入市場
So we should buy up all the vacant houses and burn them.
Dick需要一個能認清現狀的買家
Dick needs a buyer, someone with a grip on reality.
幾個月前巴克萊銀行曾表示過些許興趣
Barclays expressed some interest a couple of months ago,
但我覺得現在的股價還沒有降到他們的心理價位
but I don't think the price is low enough for them.
- 美國銀行呢?  - 有這個可能
- Bank of America?  - Possible.
Dick之前也試探過他們
Dick's put out feelers there before.
不過我們得保持低調
We have to keep it quiet, though.
因為一旦有人獲悉他們準備出售
'Cause if anyone hears that they're trying to sell
雷曼兄弟將瞬間完蛋
Lehman'll be dead within the hour.
2008年6月11日 雷曼兄弟高管緊急決策會議
在房地產業務上的投資正在毀掉整個公司
The real estate investments are killing the firm.
我們得公開承認我們犯了一些錯誤
We have to admit publically we've made some mistakes.
我們需要對高管層進行更替
We need to make a senior management change,
從而向市場表明我們的立場
signal to the market that we get it.
- 你們指的是誰?  - Joe Gregory
- Meaning what?  - Meaning Joe Gregory.
別扯淡了
Get the fuck out of here.
還輪不到你們來告訴我該如何來運營我的公司
You are not gonna tell me how to run my company.
Joe在這場危機中沒有站在你這邊 這是人所共知的
Joe hasn't had your back on risk, and everyone knows it.
Erin Callan也得走人 整條華爾街都知道她就是個笑話
Erin Callan's gotta go, too. As far as the Street's concerned, she's a joke.
Joe Gregory和我共事了30多年
Joe Gregory has been with me for 30 years.
我們只是遇到了暫時性的困難 你們就想讓我把他攆走?
And you want me to kick him to the curb because we had a bad quarter?
這不是暫時性的困難
It's not just a bad quarter.
股價已經跌到23塊了
Stock hit 23.
Skip McGee 雷曼兄弟投行部 全球區總裁
23塊啊 公司大部分員工分到的股票都是在數年內無法進行買賣的
Twenty-three. Most of our guys are paid in stock they can't sell for years.
他們損失的是過去六個月媮的淨利潤
They've lost most of their net worth over the last six months.
如果你不穩住股價 你的那些交易員們只能跑路了
You don't stabilize the price, your traders are gonna jump ship.
一群自私鬼
Selfish fucks.
Dick 不僅是銀行家和交易員們 連客戶都會抽走他們的資金
It's not just bankers and traders, Dick. Clients are pulling their money.
公司將遭遇到連鎖反應
There's gonna be a run on this bank.
消息靈通人士對財經頻道透露
Sources tell CNBC that both
雷曼兄弟的Erin Callan和Joseph Gregory已經離任
Erin Callan and Joseph Gregory are out at Lehman Brothers.
公司的主席Dick Fuld在一份聲明中稱
In a statement, the company's chairman, Dick Fuld, said
2008年8月4日
將由48歲的Bart McDade代替Gregory的位子
replacing Gregory with 48-year-old Bart McDade
Bart McDade 雷曼兄弟新總裁兼首席運營官
這是他所做過的最艱難的一個決定
has been one of the most difficult decisions he's had to make.
Dick 韓國人剛剛到達Sullivan
Dick, the Koreans just arrived at Sullivan.
我們一定要抓住這次機會
Let's go make this happen.
我覺得這會兒你最好就待在這
My take is you'd be better off staying here for now.
我們要把你打造成為"幕後人士"
We need you to be our "missing man."
由我們去談 盡最大努力去促成這筆交易
We'll go in and push the deal as far as we can,
最後再由你出面來達成這筆交易
and then we'll bring you in at the end to top it off.
好吧 聽你的
All right, fine.
很好
Okay. Okay.
我們如期來到了紐約
We are committed to our presence in New York.
但我們需要知道確切的數字
But we need to know that the underlying numbers make sense.
我們也看到了事情的發展情況
We realize how things look.
但我們的股價只是被一些做空者暫時挫傷
But our stock is getting hammered by the shorts.
它的真實價值依舊沒變
The value is still there.
我們剛剛開始談 Min還是很興奮的 但他們還沒有給出具體的數字
We just started. Min's excited, but we haven't heard the terms.
你在哪兒?
Where are you?
我剛走出會議室來接你的電話啊
I just stepped out to take the call.
快回去 要有禮貌啊
Get back in there. Don't be rude.
好的
Okay.
我們只是將你們不感興趣的那一部分資產
We simply take the assets you don't find appealing,
拆分成一個獨立的公司
spin them off into a separate company.
- 你不必買下整家銀行  - 抱歉
- You don't buy that bank.  - I'm very sorry.
你只需買下這家運營良好的銀行就行了
You buy the good bank.
他們對房地產不感興趣
Look, they don't like the real estate.
什麼叫他們不感興趣?
What do you mean, they don't like it?
Dick 我們終於有些進展了 暫時不要打擾我了
Dick, we're making real progress here, okay? Let me stay on it for now.
Min 你好
Min, how are you?
很高興見到你
Great to see you.
希望沒有打擾到你們
I don't want to interrupt.
Dick 你來得正是時候
Dick, great timing.
看起來雙方對合同的大致框架都很滿意
We seem to be in sync on the broad strokes of the deal.
我們可以回到意向書上來了嗎?
Shall we get back to the letter of intent?
Min 我不得不告訴你 我覺得你正在犯一個大錯
Min, I have to tell you, I think you're making a big mistake here.
房地產資產價值巨大
There's great value in the real estate assets.
要不通過仔細分析投資組合
How about we walk through the portfolio
我來向你展示這一點如何?
and I'll show you?
我們已經仔細看過了
We have looked at them.
有些地方你肯定沒看懂
Then you must have looked at them in the wrong way.
我不想看你做出錯誤的決定
See, I just don't wanna see you leave money on the table.
或許我們應該休息一下
Perhaps we should take a break.
Min 非常抱歉
Min, I'm so sorry.
我們一直在真心實意地進行談判 突然就這麼回到原點了?
We have negotiated in good faith. Now all of a sudden we are going backward?
我們同意你給出的報價
We can work with you on the price.
這與報價無關
It is not about the price.
我說的是你們處理事情的方式
It is about the way you have conducted this.
非常感謝大家
I'd like to thank you, all of you,
但我覺得已經沒有繼續談下去的基礎了
but I don't think we have a structure that works.
什麼 就這麼結束了?
What, that's it?
你們就打算這麼打道回府了?
You're just gonna pack up and go back to Korea?
- 你好  - Neel 我是Dick Fuld
- Hello?  - Neel, it's Dick Fuld.
聽著 如果Hank想讓我找到買家
Listen, you know, if Hank wants me to find a buyer,
你們得出面幫我一把啊
you guys need to step up and help.
韓國人剛剛退出交易了
The Koreans just walked out, okay?
我只是表達一下自己的觀點
Look, I'm just speaking for myself here,
但我認為你應該做一些有利於公司的事情
but I think you need to do what's right for the firm.
什麼叫有利於?
Do what's right?
這話是什麼意思?
What is that supposed to mean?
如果股價繼續下跌
If your stock price keeps sliding,
你也許會得到一個令人失望的報價
you may get an offer at a price that doesn't look all that compelling,
但為了公司的持續經營 你必須接受它
but you may have to take it just to keep the company intact.
你指什麼樣的買價?
What kind of price are you talking about?
可能會...
Could be...
我指 股價可能在個位數
I mean, it might be low single digits.
二月份 我們公司每股66美元
Last February, we were at 66 a share.
雷曼兄弟可不是貝爾斯登
Lehman Brothers is not Bear Stearns.
我們業績很好的 房地產會復甦的
We've got a great business. Real estate's gonna come back.
我他媽不會把這公司送人的!
I am not fucking giving this company away!
在雷曼兄弟股價因其
While the real estate market has put
房地產業務而備受壓力時
put Lehman Brothers shares under pressure,
房貸巨頭房利美和房地美兩公司傳出報道說
mortgage giants Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac stocks
需要籌資750億美元才能償付其債務
are suddenly plummeting this morning, after reports the companies
此後 這兩家公司的股價急劇下跌
may need to raise $75 billion just to remain solvent.
因為這兩家公司幾乎擔保了
Because they guarantee such an enormous percentage
全國大部分的次級貸款
of the nation's mortgages,
有關人士預測政府將會介入
there is renewed speculation that the government
該事態中 收購兩家公司
may have to step in and take them over,
政府介入的可能性也從奧巴馬的競選演講中得到證實
a possibility Barack Obama has now raised on the campaign trail.
若房利美和房地美倒閉了
If Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac collapsed,
那麼將會給整個金融界帶來
then probably the financial system would receive such a body blow
災難性的動盪
that it could be disastrous.
房地美下跌了8% 房利美下跌5%
Freddie just dropped another 8%. Fannie's down 5%.
Timothy Geithner 紐約聯邦儲備銀行行長
下跌趨勢迅猛 我們得採取措施了 立刻
There's no bottom here. We need to do something. Now.
我們正向國會提議
We're working on a proposal for Congress,
看能否批准我們向市場注資救市
see if we can get the authority to put some money in.
我本不想這麼做的 但若情況特別糟糕的話...
I'd rather not go that way, but if we get there...
我想事態已經很糟糕了
I think we're already there.
- 你能要到多少?  - 一張空白支票
- How much are you gonna ask for?  - A blank check.
投資資金必須足以讓我們挽救市場
It has to be enough of a statement to reassure the market.
得讓市場覺得 我擁有決定性武器
They need to think I've got a bazooka in my pocket.
不是說我們真的會注資 只是如果我們得到了國會的許可
I'm not saying that we use it, but if we have the authority,
那麼 所有瘋狂拋售股票的人會逐漸冷靜下來 重新參與
everyone who's dumping their shares will calm down, back off.
行 若你在國會 你也可以順便提議資助那些投資銀行 是吧?
Okay, if you're going to Congress, why don't we give to the banks, too?
因為雷曼兄弟眼看活不成了 美林也離破產不遠了
'Cause Lehman's looking like shit and Merrill's not far behind.
光說服他們願意接管房利美和房地美就夠走運了
We'll be lucky to get them to move on Fannie and Freddie.
我們只能說試試看
We do what we can do.
北京奧運會開幕式 2008年8月8日
部長先生 部長夫人 請看這邊
Secretary, Mrs. Paulson, over here.
請看這邊 謝謝
Over here, please.
Paulson部長 請看這邊 謝謝
Secretary Paulson, over here, please.
Paulson夫人 謝謝
Mrs. Paulson. Thank you.
Paulson夫人
Mr. Paulson.
Paulson部長 夫人 請看這邊 謝謝
Mr. and Mrs. Paulson, this way, please.
- 我來抱著  - 帶她先去一邊
- I've got her.  - You should take her.
請看這邊 Paulson部長 謝謝
Right over here, Secretary Paulson, please.
請笑一笑 謝謝
Big smile. Thank you.
這正是我需要的
That's just what I need.
新聞媒體拍到美國財政部長居然揮舞著中國國旗
Press photos of the Treasury Secretary waving the Chinese flag.
Paulson竟然是共產黨員 你當時臉上的表情很精彩的
Paulson the Communist. The look on your face was priceless.
Hank 關於房利美和房地美 我有問題要問
Hank, I must ask you about Fannie and Freddie.
我們在"兩房"公司投資了數十億美元
We have hundreds of billions invested.
你和我保證過投資是安全的
You've assured us the investment is safe.
是的 絕對安全
And it is, absolutely.
可我們發現 近期損失了很大一筆數額
We're watching a great deal of our money disappear.
兩個月內 股價竟然跌了60%
Share prices have dropped 60% in the last two months.
光到處宣揚你有決定性武器可以救市是不夠的
Carrying your bazooka around has not helped matters.
國會給了你權利 也許是時候使用這項權利了
Congress gave you the power. Perhaps it is time to use it.
市場會穩定下來的 需要的只是時間而已
The market will stabilize. We just have to give it some time.
俄羅斯上個月和我們聯繫
There was an approach last month from Russia.
他們也持有大量房利美和房地美的的債券
They have considerable holdings in Fannie and Freddie as well.
俄羅斯建議我和他們合作 搞一次突擊
They suggested we coordinate, and without warning,
向市場大量拋售房利美
dump hundreds of billions of Fannie
和房地美的債卷
and Freddie's bonds onto the market.
- 那市場就會...  - 一片混亂
- That would be...  - Chaos.
貴國發售過多的債卷
The amount of debt your country carries
是你們一處致命的弱點
is a terrible vulnerability.
- 但你們...  - 我們很客氣地拒絕了
- But you...  - We declined, respectfully.
即使是在美國
Even in the US, it seems
你們政府和非國營企業
the relationship between the government
的關係似乎也是挺複雜的
and private industry isn't so simple.
他在威脅我們?
Was it a threat?
不 不是 只能算一個友情提示
No, no, it was a friendly reminder
提示我們 只要他們給莫斯科打一個電話
that with a single phone call to Moscow,
我們美國經濟就會全面崩潰
they can take down the entire US economy.
從賬面來看 房利美和房地美簡直就是一團糟
The book says Fannie and Freddie are a nightmare.
負債缺口至少有數百億美元
They are in the hole easily tens of billions of dollars.
過不了幾周 他們就無法償還債務了
Another few weeks, they're gonna start defaulting on their debts.
政府得介入干預此事了
We're gonna have to step in.
我不明白該怎麼做
I don't see how we can avoid it.
看來武器不開一槍是震懾不住市場的
Turns out a bazooka's not that useful unless you fire it.
雷曼兄弟股價又跌了10%
Lehman's down another 10%.
你就不讓我安心地咬一口麵包 是吧?
You are not gonna let me get down a single bite, are you?
所以我早餐吃燕麥粥
This is why I have oatmeal.
Dick現在正滿世界地乞求援助
Dick is trotting around the world with his hat in his hands,
但就是沒人給他錢
no one will give him any money.
韓國老闆放棄了他 墨西哥人叫他別管了
Korea walked out on him. Mexico told him to shove it.
沒人對他公司感興趣 所有能忽悠到的融資早就入股了
No one's interested. All the dumb money's already in.
那找美國銀行如何? 他們還有興趣吧?
What about B of A? Are they still in the mix?
巴克萊銀行也開始蠢蠢欲動了
And Barclays is sniffing around again,
他們認為此時是買入的好時機
now that they think it's a fire sale.
- 這倒不錯  - 鬼知道
- That's promising.  - I don't know.
那些英國佬光會說說 從未付諸行動(巴克萊銀行是英國最大商業銀行之一)
The British, they do a lot of talking. They never close.
- 美國銀行是目前最好的收購者了  - 雷曼不能步貝爾斯登後塵
- B of A is still our best bet.  - This can't be another Bear.
不會的 他們會認購雷曼的全部股份
Absolutely not. They want Lehman, they buy it outright.
但他們需要我們經濟上的幫助
But they may need a little hand-holding, though.
因為他們才收購了美國國家金融服務公司 所以口袋埵麻I緊
They just bought Countrywide. They're spread a little thin.
央行對美國銀行資本充足率要求得暫時鬆一鬆
You may have to give them a break with the capital requirements.
你想讓我允許美國銀行提高他們的杠桿比率(償還財務能力比率)
You want me to allow them to raise their leverage
這樣他們就能收購另一家
so they can buy a bank that's about
因杠桿比率過高而即將破產的銀行?
to fail because it was overleveraged?
你有更好意見?
You got a better idea?
突發新聞剛剛傳來 財經頻道剛剛收到消息
Breaking news just coming in. Sources telling CNBC
政府最近宣佈接管
that the government has just taken
房利美和房地美公司
control of Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac.
然而在七月份 您可能會記起 Hank Paulson曾說過
Back in July, you remember, Hank Paulson said
他想讓通過此舉來介入
that he wanted the power to step in,
但他可能不會採取行動
but he probably wouldn't use it.
現在看來Paulson
It certainly sounds like Paulson
不得不用起他手堛漯Z器了
just pulled the trigger on that bazooka.
雖然房利美和房地美公司正在進行國有化
Despite the move to nationalize Fannie and Freddie,
2008年9月11號 紐約市區
但股市仍然全盤處於下跌狀態
the market is still in negative territory across the board.
投資者們現在正關注雷曼兄弟的命運
Investors now focusing their attention on Lehman Brothers,
尤其是有傳言說 這家美國
amid fresh reports that the nation's
第四大投資銀行
fourth-largest investment bank
正處於破產邊緣
may be on the brink of bankruptcy.
嘿 Rodge
Rodge.
你好 Chris
Chris.
今天帶錢來了 對吧?
Bring your money today, huh?
Chris Flowers 銀行收購專家
別讓Fuld再隱藏什麼對公司不好的消息了
Make sure Fuld's not keeping any bad news out of the mix.
用Dick的話來說就是"大白於天下"
It's "open kimono," to quote Dick.
Rodgin Cohen 雷曼兄弟辯護律師
他讓人討厭
There's a revolting image.
你研究他們的數據了嗎?
Did, uh, you get a look at the numbers?
房地產資產是個問題 他們對其定價300億美元
The real estate's the issue. They got it marked at 30 billion.
估計高估了一半 別這麼緊張
It's worth maybe half of that. Don't look so nervous.
你們只需要花買一個熱狗的錢
You're about to get a Wall Street
就能買到這家華爾街的投資銀行
bank for the price of a hot dog.
Greg Curl 美國銀行策劃部部長
我知道Paulson和Ken Lewis(美國銀行首席執行官)
I know that Paulson told Ken Lewis
說過他不會介入此收購的
that he's not gonna pay for this.
若政府不出面接管一些不良資產的話
And I don't see how we can do it
我想我們還是無法收購雷曼的
unless the government takes some of the downside.
Paulson只是故作姿態
Paulson is posturing.
他會給你支票的 就像他曾讓摩根大通
He'll write a check just like he did
收購貝爾斯登時一樣
for Jamie Dimon on the Bear deal.
他必須這麼做
He has to.
他可不能在總統競選年度再損失一家大型投行了
He can't lose another major bank in an election year.
而且 那傢伙在高盛的時候
Besides, the guy made, like, a half
最起碼賺了五億美元
a billion bucks at Goldman Sachs.
他讓雷曼兄弟倒閉? 讓高盛最強的競爭對手倒閉?
He lets Lehman die? Goldman's biggest competitor?
那會讓人懷疑他還是高盛的人呢
Makes him look like he's still working for Goldman.
我估計他這會兒正在財政部寫支票呢
He's just doing it out of a desk at Treasury.
甜甜圈在哪?
Where are the donuts?
就是如此 若你是他們這些金融企業的首席執行官
Exactly. If you're the CEO of one of these financial firms,
你早就注意到政府願意支援你收購的話
you've already seen what the government was willing to do.
那你可以堂而皇之地說
Why wouldn't you play chicken with them and say,
"當然 我們願意協助你們 可你得給我點好處吧?
"Sure, I'll help you out. But you gotta throw in a sweetener,
就像你援助別人收購時所作的"
just like you did for those guys"?
公眾以為我們會資助Dick Fuld
They just assume I'm gonna bail out Dick Fuld,
以為我是那個為他們業績不好擦屁股的人
like I'm the guy behind the elephant with the shovel.
公眾認為雷曼兄弟這次被收購就像
They're all drawing a line from Bear
貝爾斯登 房利美和房地美一樣
and Fannie and Freddie right to Lehman.
不會有納稅人再願意支持資助另一家破產銀行了
There's no way the taxpayers are gonna go for another bailout.
一攬子大規模收購援助政策
Very large purchase assistance package.
這次必須讓他們自己去解決了
We need to come up with a private-sector solution,
讓他們投行自己去彌補負債缺口
get the investment banks to bridge the gap.
可以 但除非他們確信您不會再
Okay, but that's never gonna work
支援該收購行動 否則行不通
unless they believe that you've drawn a line.
我知道您不喜歡向公眾洩露消息 讓我們和媒體交流
I know you don't like leaking, but let us reach out to the press.
好
Okay.
Flowers先生 您有電話
Mr. Flowers, there's a call for you.
是美國國際集團的Bob Willumstad 他堅持一定要與您通話
Bob Willumstad from AIG. He's very insistent.
Robert Willumstad 美國國際集團首席執行官
Flowers先生 我的人說你是這方面的專家
Mr. Flowers. My people tell me you're the man to talk to.
我們公司面臨一個大問題
We've got a real problem here.
嗯? 什麼樣的問題?
Yeah? What kind of problem?
似乎我們的現金流就快斷了
It looks very much like we are about to run out of cash.
美國國際集團?
AIG?
我們給您發了一份文件 是一份電子錶格
We've sent over a document. It's a spreadsheet.
當然 這是一份機密文件 但會讓您瞭解我們的困境的
It's confidential, of course, but it might give you some insight.
我正在處理雷曼兄弟的事情 美國銀行要收購他們
I'm in the middle of Lehman. I'm working with B of A.
那您明天能過來一下嗎?
Is there any way you could come over tomorrow?
我會研究下這張表 然後再說吧
I'll take a look at the numbers and we'll talk.
Flowers先生
Mr. Flowers.
誰去開下電視
Somebody put the TV on.
財經頻道在說雷曼兄弟
CNBC's talking about Lehman.
一位熟悉Paulson的...
A person familiar with Paulson's...
一位瞭解財政部長Hank Paulson想法的人透露
Treasury Secretary Hank Paulson's thinking,
在目前這種經濟環境下
and he is saying there will be no government money
政府不會資助美國銀行收購雷曼兄弟
in the resolution of this situation.
他們說雷曼兄弟被收購和貝爾斯登的情況有兩處不同
They're saying two things make the Lehman deal different.
雷曼兄弟收購是市場早已預料到的 並有半年時間
The market's been aware and had time to prepare
可以準備 第二點是...
for over six months. And the second is...
只是電視台在胡扯?
Is that just TV bullshit?
還是Paulson想給我們傳遞的信息?
Or is that Paulson sending us a message?
喂 Chris?
Chris?
什麼? 不好意思
Yeah? Sorry.
"一位財政部部長的朋友"
What exactly does "a person familiar
這到底是什麼意思?
with the Treasury Secretary" mean?
可能有很多的含義
That could mean a lot of things.
是你的某位員工胡言亂語吧?
Did one of your staffers do this?
一定是你十分鐘前解雇了誰吧
Please tell me someone got fired 10 minutes ago.
那是我的意思
The leak came from me.
Hank 你那種公眾宣言
Hank, a public statement like that
可能會引起很多想像不到的災難
can have a lot of unintended consequences.
我們得提醒別的銀行
We had to send a message to the other banks.
讓他們自己解決了
They need to step up.
我的帽子埵A也變不出兔子來了
I don't have another rabbit I can pull out of my hat.
Rodgin Cohen剛打電話給我
Rodgin Cohen just called me.
他說美國銀行的收購團現在
The B of A team is sitting there
坐在那邊在手機上玩打磚塊
playing Brickbreaker on their phones.
他們不想收購了
They don't want this deal.
收購暫停是因為
The deal is hanging by a thread because
他們對雷曼調查得越仔細
the closer they get to Lehman,
就越覺得 這其實是一個廢料排放場
the more it looks like a toxic waste dump.
所以我們得為他們收購做風險上的補償
Which is why at the end of the day we may have to help them,
若您不作出那種公眾宣言的話 這場收購本該是很順利的...
which would be a lot easier if we didn't publicly state that...
我們不能 Tim! 那樣做不合法!
We can't, Tim! Legally, we can't!
若要合法地做 那這場災難我們也沒辦法阻止
Legally, we haven't figured out how yet.
我很擔心
I am concerned
因為我們現在還有幾種挽救措施 但我們正在
we are limiting our options at a time when we have very few,
浪費他們
if any, available.
我想讓那些首席執行官聚集到一起 給他們一個週末的時間
I want all the CEOs in a room. We've got the weekend.
把他們關在美聯儲
We lock them in a room at the Fed
在他們自己解決雷曼兄弟這爛攤子之前 不放他們出來
and we don't let them out until they have a solution on Lehman.
你的燕麥粥快涼了
Your oatmeal's getting cold.
他們會明白事態嚴重性的 他們自己會掏錢的
They'll figure it out. They'll all throw in some money.
Tim強烈建議我們
Tim is advocating strongly that we
央行出面提供一些支援
reconsider some kind of Fed support.
他想讓我們資助所有人
Tim wants us to pick up the tab on everyone.
我可不想做"破產救援大使"
I can't be Mr. Bailout.
而且雷曼兄弟的虧損是貝爾斯登的兩倍
The Lehman hole is twice what Bear's was.
而且投資者正急著從中抽身出來
Investors are pulling their accounts.
你想長期借貸給他們嗎?
You want to lend into a run?
那巴克萊銀行呢? 他們仍想收購雷曼嗎?
What about Barclays? Are they still interested?
他們在對待風險上比美國銀行更加保守
They can't afford the risk any more than B of A can.
我相信你一定能夠說服任何人掏出錢
I don't doubt your ability to talk anybody into submission,
但是這風險確實很大
but it is still a long shot.
而且雷曼兄弟很可能會破產
And there's a very real possibility that Lehman goes under.
這周將會有場收購談判
There's a deal to be made here.
這場談判一定會成功的
I'm gonna make the deal.
在收盤前不到一小時
With just a little more than an hour left until the market
雷曼兄弟的股價又猛跌了一把
closes, shares of Lehman Brothers have taken another tumble.
股價跌到新低 每股4美元都不到了
The stock is now trading at a new low, under $4 a share.
而且從賣方形勢來看
And judging from the selling,
這種下跌趨勢仍會繼續
there doesn't appear to be a bottom in sight.
除了Blankfein(高盛首席執行官)說他有一場演講 會盡量趕過來的
So, Blankfein has a speech he's trying to get out of,
其他的人都同意了
but the rest have confirmed.
- 告訴他必須來參加  - 好的
- Tell him it's not optional.  - Yeah.
Christopher Cox 美國證交會主席
下午好 主席 歡迎來參加該次會議
Good afternoon, Chairman. Thank you so much for joining us.
- 這架是誰的飛機?  - 呃 這是租來的
- Whose plane is this?  - Uh, that's a rental.
Hank自己掏錢的
Hank put it on his card.
先生 你認識Neel 這是Michele Davis負責公眾事務
Sir, you know Neel and Michele Davis, Public Affairs.
嗨 很高興見面
Hi. Pleasure.
- 這位是Dan Jester 我們團隊的新人  - 你好
- This is Dan Jester, our new numbers guy.  - Hi.
是我勸他退休後繼續出來工作的
I talked him into coming out of retirement.
- 什麼? 退休?  - 我們以前在高盛是同事
- Excuse me? Retirement?  - He was with us at Goldman.
財政部還有沒有員工不是從高盛過來的?
Got anybody at Treasury who wasn't at Goldman?
主席 有一點必須澄清一下
Chairman, just to be clear,
我們財政部和高盛之間沒有任何利益衝突
there's no question of conflict of interest.
Hank在任職前就將高盛所有的股份拋售了
Hank sold all of his Goldman stock before he took office.
- 我什麼也沒暗示  - 不好意思
- I wasn't implying anything.  - Sorry.
我們對外面所傳的"高盛政府"的謠言比較敏感
We're a little touchy about the whole "Government Sachs" thing.
我們走吧?
Shall we?
美國銀行發現雷曼的不良資產越來越多
B of A keeps finding more toxic assets.
他們需要政府介入模仿之前摩根大通的收購
They want you to reconsider a Jamie deal.
他們會承擔10億元的損失
They'll split the first billion in losses,
剩餘的40億損失的由政府提供擔保
but they want you on the hook for the next 40.
就像你對貝爾斯登收購做的一樣
You did it for Bear.
Greg 我過會打給你
Greg, let me get back to you.
難道我得在我額頭上紋個字才行嗎?
What, do I have to tattoo it on my forehead?
我們不會對雷曼兄弟收購提供一分錢
We are not bailing out Lehman.
這是華爾街自己賭博失敗
Wall Street has a gambling problem.
若老是讓政府為他們擦屁股
If government keeps covering their losses,
他們永遠也得不到教訓
they never learn anything.
- 怎麼了?  - 我不知道您是想繼續
- What?  - I didn't know if you wanted
教導我道德危機
to keep lecturing me on moral hazard
還是想讓我拒絕美國銀行提議
or if I should just call B of A back.
我們只能讓他們都坐在一起 進行討論
We need to keep them at the table
直到這些企業找到自己的解決方法
until they come up with a private-sector solution.
告訴他們最好照我說的做
Tell them to stay with us.
- Alistair 你好啊  - 你好 Henry
- Alistair, hello.  - Hello, Henry.
請等一下
Hold on one second.
英國財政大臣打來的
Chancellor of the Exchequer.
我瞭解到巴克萊銀行想收購雷曼兄弟
I understand Barclays is one of your potential buyers for Lehman.
但我國的銀行最近的資金壓力也很大
My banks are already under a great deal of stress.
我可不想承擔過多義務
I don't want to become overextended.
雷曼兄弟雖然最近出了問題 但還是有價值的
Lehman is problematic, but there's value there.
我們會讓他能夠盈利的 繼續保持合作吧
We will find a way to make it attractive. Just stay with us.
那再說吧
Talk soon then.
再見
Bye.
2008年9月18日 星期五
我們不會拒絕巴克萊銀行 但最好還是由美國銀行來收購
We'll keep Barclays in the mix, but B of A is still our best bet.
我們今晚會召集所有主要銀行的首席執行官過來開會
We've got the CEOs of every major bank coming here tonight.
我們得明白地告訴他們 這是他們自己捅的簍子
We have to make it clear that this is their problem,
我們政府可以做顧問或是盟友
that we are their advisors and their allies,
但我們不是他們的保險箱
but we are not their safety net.
對這些人 我們還能指望什麼呢?
What should we expect from these guys?
紐約 美聯儲
Jamie很聰明
Jamie is smart.
他買下貝爾斯登後 手頭可運作的資金就不多了
He doesn't have as much cash to work with since he bought Bear.
Jamie Dimon 摩根大通主席兼首席執行官
Lloyd是巨星
Lloyd's a superstar.
高盛是華爾街上最精明的一家
Goldman's the smartest shop on the Block.
雖然我之前當過他老闆 但那並不表示 他就會聽我的了
And just because I used to be his boss, it doesn't mean he's gonna listen to me.
Lloyd Blackfein 高盛主席兼首席執行官
John Mack 他過去常常滿樓層東奔西跑 大呼小叫
John Mack, he used to run around the floor screaming,
"水埵釵撠! 我們殺啊!"
"There's blood in the water! Let's go kill someone!"
他是好戰分子
He's a fighter.
John Mack 摩根士丹利主席兼首席執行官
Thain是我在高盛的副手 他很自私 是個實用主義者
Thain was my number two at Goldman. He's selfish. He's a pragmatist.
他知道 如果雷曼兄弟倒了 下一個就輪到美林證券了
He knows if Lehman goes, Merrill's next.
John Thain 美林證券主席兼首席執行官
Vikram Pandit剛入職花旗
Vikram Pandit is the new guy at Citigroup.
沒人知道 是他在運作花旗 還是花旗在運作他
No one knows if he's running Citi or if Citi's running him.
Vikram Pandit 花旗集團首席執行官
感謝各位匆忙之中趕來這
Thanks for coming down here on such short notice.
下週一早上 雷曼兄弟將無法償付其債務
Monday morning, Lehman will no longer be able to honor its obligations.
有兩家有意購買 美國銀行和巴克萊銀行
We have two potential buyers. B of A and Barclays.
但如果沒有第三方融資 它們都無法完成收購
Neither will take the company unless someone else finances part of the deal.
政府不會進行干預
The government is not in a position to step in.
上一次是最後一次 這次就由你們完成了
I did the last one. You're gonna do this one.
Dick Fuld在哪兒?
Where's Dick Fuld?
Dick不適合再做決定了
Dick's in no condition to make any decisions.
我們將各位分成三組
We're breaking you into three groups.
第一組 評估雷曼兄弟的不良資產
The first one will try to value Lehman's toxic assets.
第二組 設計投資架構 讓大家都可以投資雷曼
The second one will work on some sort of structure for you all to invest in Lehman.
第三組 制定熄燈計劃
And the third one works on the lights-out plan.
如果雷曼兄弟申請破產 我們需要考慮
If Lehman files for bankruptcy, we need to figure out
如何遏制對各家的損害
how to contain the damage to the rest of you.
天吶
Christ.
我們早就預見到會出現這種狀況
We've all seen this coming for miles.
我認為 雷曼兄弟即使破產 也不會給我們公司帶來太大影響
I don't think a Lehman bankruptcy takes down our firms.
所以呢 我們就只能祝福雷曼了嗎?
What, are we crossing our fingers?
這是要求我們挽救競爭對手 別表現得好像在幫我們一樣
You're asking us to save a competitor. Let's not act like you're doing us a favor.
各位 各位 大家都是偉大的美國人
Gentlemen, gentlemen, you are great Americans
這是承擔我們的愛國責任
undertaking a patriotic duty.
各位的努力將為自身贏得
Your travail will earn you the love
舉國的愛戴和感激
and gratitude of your country.
我記得 Thomas Paine(激進民主主義者)曾經說過 "這些..."
I think it was Thomas Paine who said, "These are..."
雷曼兄弟是在座各家銀行的合作夥伴
Lehman is a trading partner for every bank in this room.
它的破產將對大家都有很大衝擊
Their failure will be a massive blow to all of you.
這就是重點
This is your problem.
我們可以好好說說 為何會到如此地步
We can all argue about how we got here.
放鬆管制 衍生品 Dick Fuld決策不利
Deregulation, derivatives, Dick Fuld made bad decisions.
我們都有責任 這是災難性的動盪
We're all responsible. It's a catastrophic mess.
政府已經竭盡所能 現在全靠你們了
The government's done whatever it can do. It's on you now.
各位該解決問題 付出代價了
You need to fix it and you need to pay for it.
我就直說了
Let me be clear.
沒出力的人 我們會記下的
We will remember anyone who is not helpful.
2008年9月13日 星期六
你注意到這其中的小規律了嗎?
Do you notice a little pattern here?
不見棺材不掉淚
We don't deal with things until there's some kind of emergency on the table.
是啊 不到最後一刻 沒人會去處理的
Yeah, we don't deal with things until Friday.
現在一隻腳已經踏進去了
Some kind of a weekend thing.
我們什麼時候才能
When were we gonna figure out
找到解決投資銀行的破產問題的好方法?
exactly how to handle the failure of an investment bank?
週末搞定吧
Let's do it over a weekend.
我剛剛跟一位密切關注現狀的專家談過
I talked to a person who is monitoring the situation out there,
他說 業界人士都期望 他們能和Jamie Dimon一樣 得到政府的自助
and the person said they all want the same deal Jamie Dimon got,
但預計期望會落空
and they're not going to get it.
提醒一句 Chris Flowers正在大廳
Just a heads up, Chris Flowers is in the lobby.
他是美國銀行收購雷曼案的顧問
He's consulting for B of A on Lehman.
Hank之前將Flowers擠出了高盛
Hank pushed Flowers out of Goldman.
昨天我們還認為雷曼的不良資產僅300億 今天就漲到了700億
Yesterday, we thought Lehman was holding 30 billion in crap. Today it's 70.
700億不良資產 這還只是隨機抽樣
$70 billion in assets that we're valuing with a dartboard.
沒事 我們會解決這個問題
No, we're gonna work this out.
除非政府干預 不然我們就停手
Unless you step in, we're ending this.
別忘了Dick
Don't forget about Dick.
好了 Dick Fuld不停打來電話 不停要求我們提高價格
Yeah, Dick Fuld keeps calling, hammering us to raise the price.
抱歉
Excuse me.
700億不良資產 還無擔保?
70 fucking billion and no collateral?
如果雷曼兄弟本週末破產
If Lehman Brothers fails this weekend,
專家們毫不懷疑 下一個將是美林證券
there's little doubt amongst the people I speak to that Merrill Lynch will be next.
信心是非常脆弱的
Confidence is a very fragile thing.
在金融市場 信心的流失速度非常快
And in our financial markets, it is eroding very quickly.
雷曼撐不下去了 我們就是下一個 必須立刻採取措施了
Lehman's not gonna make it. We're next. We need to do something right now.
只有美國銀行能救我們了 我可以打個電話看看
B of A's the only one out there. I can put in a call.
- 雖然這樣會毀了雷曼 不過...  - 雷曼是自食其果
- It screws Lehman, but...  - Lehman screwed themselves.
Paulson已經劃定了底線 雷曼完了 打電話吧
Paulson has drawn a line in the sand. Lehman is dead. Make the call.
你們考慮一下收購美林的股份吧
We'd like you guys to look at taking a stake in Merrill,
有約10%的利潤
something in the neighborhood of 10%.
我不知道能否拿到10%的利潤
I don't know if I can generate any interest in 10%,
不過如果是收購整家公司的話
but if the whole company's in play,
我們肯定是願意考慮一下的
I bet that's something that we'd consider.
我們和雷曼?
Us and Lehman?
這種規模的收購 我們只能完成一家
Deal this size, there's only room for one.
毫無疑問 風險很大 但是只要各位不中途退出
It is a lot of risk, no question, but if you stay in the game,
- 就都能找到各自的解決之道  - 當然了
- we all will find a private solution.  - Absolutely.
別被這些數字嚇到了 我們會解決的 雷曼是值得收購的
Don't get scared by the numbers. We'll figure it out. Lehman is worth owning.
各位 有空嗎?
Guys, you got a second?
我昨天去過了美國國際集團
I was at AIG yesterday.
下週三 他們將有至少50億的缺口
Next Wednesday, they got a $5 billion hole, minimum.
我跟沃倫·巴菲特聯繫過了 他表示絕對不會幫忙
I called Warren Buffett. He wouldn't touch it with a stick.
我們會調查清楚
We're looking into it.
這是一家非常大的公司
It's a very big company.
謝了 Chris 感謝你所有的幫助
Thanks, Chris. I appreciate all your help.
他們根本不瞭解狀況
They're not on top of it.
看看這個
Look at this.
這可能嗎?
Is this even possible?
美國國際集團?
AIG?
該死的
Holy shit.
調查清楚
Get into this.
嘿 John
John.
你明白現在的狀況嗎?
Do you see what's happening here?
你想好怎麼為自己打算了嗎?
Are you watching out for yourself?
我不笨 我正在採取行動
I'm not thick. I'm working on something.
你想去找美國銀行
You're talking to B of A.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我知道 這樣對雷曼不好 但是我必須先顧好美林
I know it's not good for Lehman, but I have to take care of Merrill.
把雷曼扔給我來操心
Let me worry about Lehman.
巴克萊還沒有退出
Barclays is still in the game.
你去搞定吧
Just get it done.
美國銀行將收購美林
B of A is gonna buy Merrill.
我們必須讓巴克萊出手
We need to make Barclays work.
我記得你說過 英國佬只說不做的
I thought you said the British never close.
他們就在外面 似乎真的很想收購
They're here. They seem to really want it.
只要我們主動一點 他們就會收購的
If we hold their hands, they'll close.
Rodgin 怎麼回事? Geithner不接電話 Paulson也不接電話
Rodgin, what the fuck? I can't get Geithner. I can't get Paulson.
連我的手下現在也不接電話了
I can't even get my own goddamn employees to pick up the phone.
Dick 大家都太忙了
There's a lot happening down here, Dick.
噢 該死
Oh, fuck.
給我聽好 你去告訴Geithner
You know what? You tell Geithner,
他要是不幫我把這事解決了 下一個就輪到美林了
he doesn't pull my ass out of the fire, Merrill's gonna be next.
他知道
He knows that.
Dick 他剛告訴我 他們正在為美林尋找出路
Dick, he just told me they're working on a solution for Merrill.
那群混蛋要去幫美林?
Those cocksuckers are gonna bail out Merrill?
不 不是美聯儲
No, no, not the Fed.
沒有私營買家了 只有美國銀行和...
There's no private buyers. There's just B of A and...
他們想讓美國銀行收購美林?
They're gonna put B of A together with Merrill?
還有巴克萊銀行 Hank覺得...
We still have Barclays. Hank feels that...
聯邦政府竟然給我幫倒忙?
The federal government is snaking my deal?
我簡直不敢相信!
I cannot fucking believe this shit!
美國銀行和美林達成協議了?
B of A made a deal with Merrill?
對 雷曼的問題還是沒解決
Yeah, Lehman's still our problem.
2008年9月14日
再來這麼一次 我可受不了了
I don't think I can take another day of this.
你是剛下梅賽德斯 來到紐約美聯儲
You're getting out of a Mercedes to go to the New York Federal Reserve.
可不是奧馬哈海灘的希金斯快艇
It's not a Higgins boat on Omaha Beach.
好了 好了 時間已經夠長了
Okay, okay, we've been here a long time.
別廢話了
Let's stop fucking around.
政府想讓華爾街付賬
Main Street wants Wall Street to pay.
他們覺得 我們就是有錢的笨蛋
They think we're overpaid assholes.
沒有哪條政策規定 一定要參與緊急援助
There's no politician who's gonna sign off on a bailout.
那為什麼不去資助那些賺錢的人呢?
Why would you bail out people whose sole job is to make money?
簡單點說一下現在的狀況吧
So, let's make this real simple.
Hank認為 他可以把雷曼好的資產出售給巴克萊銀行
Hank thinks he can sell the good parts of Lehman to Barclays,
但這樣就得有人把拖垮這家公司的抵押房產接手下來
but someone has to take the real estate crap that's weighing down the company.
誰都不知道這些不良資產的價值
Nobody knows how much this shit is worth,
但我們很清楚 一定得有人買下這批資產 以完成收購
but we know somebody has to buy it to make a deal.
我不喜歡這樣 沒人喜歡這樣
I don't like it. Nobody likes it.
那就別抱怨了 去做吧
Let's just suck it up and do it.
有多少人可以投個10億元 阻止雷曼的頹勢?
How many of you can kick in a billion dollars to stop Lehman from going down?
我投 10億
I'm in. One billion.
好
Okay.
高盛投10億
Goldman's in for a billion.
John 你呢?
John?
喂?
Yeah?
是
Yes.
好
Yeah.
是
Yes.
成功了 巴克萊銀行願意購買
We did it. Barclays came through.
太棒了!
Too goddamn right!
巴克萊不願意要不動產資產 但是其他銀行同意收購這部分了
Barclays won't touch the real estate assets, but the other banks agreed to cover those.
通知董事會 把大家都喊來 我們有交易要談了
Call the board. Get everybody here. We got a deal to make.
好的
Okay.
晚上9點 倫敦
找到他了嗎?
Did you get him?
Geithner不回我電話
Geithner doesn't return my calls.
我們一個人都找不到
We can't get hold of any of those people.
今天之前 沒有我們發話 他們是簽不了協議的
At the end of the day, they can't sign the deal without our say-so.
對 但是他們知道嗎?
Yes, but do they know that?
對
Yes.
Callum McCarthy爵士 英國銀監會主席
嗯 一定 既然他屈尊來電 那就放他一馬吧
Yes, by all means, now that he deigns to call, put him through.
Callum爵士 抱歉沒能回電
Sir Callum, sorry I haven't gotten back to you.
我們在處理巴克萊銀行收購雷曼的事宜
We're just sorting through this Barclays deal for Lehman.
身為巴克萊銀行的監管方
As Barclays' regulator,
我們非常關注這樁計劃中的交易
we have serious concerns about this proposed arrangement.
什麼? 你是說你不同意這樁交易?
What? Are you saying you won't approve the deal?
就算我們同意這樁交易 事實上並非如此
Even if we were comfortable with the agreement, which we are not,
巴克萊銀行也需要至少提前30天徵得股東同意
Barclays would need at least 30 days for shareholder approval.
不 不 不 他不能 他不能這樣做
No, no, no, no, no, no. He can't. He can't do this.
- 他們能阻止交易嗎?  - 是的 當然可以了
- Can they stop the deal?  - Yeah, of course they can stop the deal.
不過就算他們阻止不了 光是耽擱一下 雷曼也完了
But even if they don't stop it, the delay will kill it.
立刻給英國財政大臣打電話
Let's call the Chancellor of the Exchequer right now.
巴克萊銀行絕對不會接受任何不良資產
None of those assets would be part of Barclays.
是 但是如果英國金融服務管理局要...
Yes, but if the FSA were to...
我們需要穩定的局勢
We need stability.
當然
Of course.
對英國金融系統而言 它也是 你們肯定發現了
must be to the British financial system. Surely you see that.
當然
Yeah.
晚安 好運
I wish you good night and good luck.
晚安
Good night to you, too.
"我們不會引入你們的癌癥"
"We don't want to import your cancer."
各位
Those of you
不想幫助巴克萊收購案的人
who didn't want to assist the Barclays deal,
現在可以鬆一口氣了
you can breathe a sigh of relief.
交易取消
The deal's not gonna happen.
- 嘿 我們籌到錢了  - 交易沒了
- Hey, we have the money.  - Deal's dead.
巴克萊的監管方不願簽字
British regulator won't sign off.
你們可以施壓啊
There must be some pressure you can exert.
相信我 我已經盡力了
Trust me, I've done everything I can.
英國佬
The British,
耍了我們
they grin-fucked us.
Paulson有10萬僱員 Geithner有200名律師
Paulson's got 100,000 employees. Geithner has 200 lawyers.
該死的Chris Cox有3千手下
Frigging Chris Cox has 3,000 people.
這群混蛋就沒一個人拿起話筒
Not a single one of those assholes could pick up a phone,
給英國佬打電話 趁他們還沒在週末剝削完我們的資金前
call the British, find out if there was a deal to be made
看看能不能搞定這樁交易?
before they spend the weekend sweating us for cash?
有人失誤了
Somebody dropped the ball.
他們不是失誤
They didn't drop the ball.
是有意犯錯 激怒高管
They dropped the ball, kicked the coach in the nuts
故意把事情搞得一團糟
and took a crap in the quarterback's mouth.
當然
Of course.
聯邦政府會有所行動
The Fed will do something.
必須的
They have to.
我們要馬上對外宣佈 雷曼破產的消息
We've got to announce the Lehman bankruptcy now.
如果亞洲股市開盤 收購案還沒敲定 大家都要做最壞的打算
If Asia opens and this isn't locked down, everyone's gonna assume the worst.
證券跌價會導致美國銀行收購美林的失敗
The sell-off will kill the Merrill-B of A deal.
- 誰去發佈公告?  - 我想應該有美國證監會來
- Who's gonna make the announcement?  - I think it's gotta be SEC.
對
Yeah.
好
Okay.
那就決定了 什麼時候開始行動?
Let's do it here. How soon can we set that up?
現在
Right away.
我們可以用主樓層 門廳那
We could use the main floor, the entrance hall.
我後面還能有雕像? 很棒
With the statue behind me? Excellent.
雷曼真的同意申請破產了?
Did Lehman actually agree to file?
Chris 給雷曼打電話
Chris, call Lehman.
確保他們馬上申請
Make sure they file right now.
一定
Absolutely.
美國國際集團是個大麻煩
AIG's a huge problem.
賬目一團亂 不過我現在可以告訴你
The books are a mess. But from what I can tell,
世界上一半的銀行和這群傢伙有關聯
half the banks in the world are in bed with these guys.
所有做過按揭抵押的銀行
Everyone who had a piece-of-crap mortgage security
都在美國國際集團為其風險投過保 我是說所有
bought insurance on their risk from AIG, and I mean everyone.
他們怎麼能讓這種事發生?
How could they let this happen?
他們肯定是覺得 房地產市場不會崩塌 絕不會
They must have figured real estate would never go down, ever.
Hank 雷曼還沒申請
Hank, Lehman still hasn't filed.
Cox必須要發佈公告了 亞洲股市要開盤了
Cox has to make his announcement. Asia's opening.
他和他們談過了嗎?
Has he talked to them?
他根本還沒打
He hasn't even called yet.
我們把巴克萊的事告訴了Fuld 我們說Cox會打電話給他
We told Fuld about Barclays. We said Cox was gonna call.
他就讓所有股東坐在那 不許接電話
He's got his entire board sitting there, no call.
Cox拒不開口
Cox is like a deer in the headlights.
混賬!
Son of a bitch!
你是他們的監管方 馬上給雷曼董事會打電話
You are their regulator. Call the Lehman board now.
Hank 現在的情況非常複雜...
Hank, it's a complicated situation where...
亞洲要開盤了
Asia's opening.
他們不公告 市場就完了
They don't announce, the market goes in the toilet.
我們必須考慮政府在其中扮演何種角色才比較恰當
We have to consider the appropriate role of government here.
我身為證監會主席 能否提議...
Can I, as Chairman of SEC, move forward and...
你們就像是不能出面的幕後人
You guys are like the gang that can't shoot straight.
這就是你們的工作
This is your job.
趕緊去打電話
Make the damn phone call.
Chris 我是Dick Fuld
Chris, this is Dick Fuld.
董事會成員正在開會 大家都到齊了 所有的股東和公司的法律顧問
The board is in session. Everyone is here. All the directors and the firm's counsel.
我們明白和巴克萊的談判已經失敗
We understand the Barclays deal has imploded.
我們在想你們有沒有我們還沒想到的解決方案
We were hoping you might have some option that we haven't thought of yet.
你知道 市場現在處於一團亂的狀態
Um, the markets are in turmoil, as you know.
我相信 雷曼兄弟的破產
A Lehman bankruptcy will help
有助於消除不穩定性因素 起到穩定市場的作用
settle that uncertainty and, we believe, calm the market.
不管是聯邦政府還是證監會都同意了
Both the Fed and SEC are in agreement about this.
讓我...  不好意思 我來說說看看我是不是理解了
Let me... I'm sorry, let me see if I understand this.
你是想命令我們使雷曼兄弟破產嗎?
Are you directing us to put Lehman into bankruptcy?
給我們幾分鐘
Give us a moment.
- 他們靜音了  - 這是怎麼回事?
- He's muted.  - What the hell was that?
讓他們去申請破產
Tell them to file.
任何在本次會議上的發言會被作為公共記錄
Everything said in that meeting is or will be public record.
我不能命令一家私人公司申請破產
I can't tell a private company to file for bankruptcy.
我沒這權利的吧?
I don't have that power. Do I?
去做
Do it.
董事會需要做出一個決定 提出破產保護的申請
The decision to file for bankruptcy protection is one the board needs to make.
這並非政府的決定 但我們相信
It is not the government's decision. But we do believe
必須有人來解決問題
that the situation should be resolved.
所以你不是在命令我們申請?
So you're not directing us to file?
我要說的就這麼多了 謝謝
I'm not saying anything more than I've just said. Thank you.
投票吧
Take the vote.
- Akers先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Akers?  - Yes.
Christopher先生?
Sir Christopher?
同意
Yes.
Admiral Evans呢?
Admiral Evans?
很遺憾 我同意
I'm sorry, but yes.
Chairman Fuld呢?
Chairman Fuld?
Dick呢?
Dick?
同意
Yes.
- Hernandez先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Hernandez?  - Yes.
- Ainslie先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Ainslie?  - Yes.
- Berlind先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Berlind?  - Yes.
- Cruikshank先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Cruikshank?  - Yes.
- Kaufman博士?  - 同意
- Dr. Kaufman?  - Yes.
- Macomber先生?  - 同意
- Mr. Macomber?  - Yes.
是P嗎?
P?
- 雷曼完蛋了  - 哦 親愛的
- Lehman's gone.  - Oh, honey.
我本該料到英國那邊會出問題的
I should have known the British were gonna be a problem.
兩天前我和他們談過 那時我應該察覺出言下之意的
I spoke to them two days ago. I should have read between the lines.
你不能獨自承受一切 這件事涉及了太多人
You can't take all this on. There's a lot of other people involved.
是我的問題 因為我是財政部長
It's on me. I'm Treasury Secretary
在我的監管下 我國第四大投資銀行
and the fourth-largest investment bank in the country
倒閉了
failed on my watch.
我是說...
I mean...
我不知道將來會發生什麼
I don't know what's gonna happen.
我也想你
Miss you, too.
2008年9月15日 週一  早上6:30
喲 出租車!
Yo, taxi!
亞洲股市大幅下跌收市
專家稱:"Paulson終於讓華爾街變得一文不值"
Jim 我現在在市中心
Jim, I'm in midtown.
電子指示器在...
The ticker is...
我看到的究竟是什麼?
What the hell am I looking at?
Hank 沒事
Hank, it's good.
"財政部和聯邦儲備局
"It is oddly reassuring
放棄雷曼兄弟的決定
"that the Treasury Department and the Federal Reserve
意想不到地讓人感到舒心"
let Lehman Brothers fail."
好的 這條 這條
Okay, here it is. Here it is.
"政府的介入會被解讀成
"Government intervention would have been seen
全球金融體系正處於極度動盪中
"as a sign of extreme peril in the global financial system
或是聯邦管理當局的監管不力的標誌
"or extreme weakness on the part of federal regulators."
該死的紐約時報
The New York fucking Times.
是啊 不僅是他們 每個人都這麼說
Yeah, and it's not just them. It's everybody.
謝謝 議員 很感激你
Thank you, Senator. I appreciate it.
議會很喜歡
Congress is liking it.
我倒是不太確定他們是不是真這麼高興
I'm not sure they should be so happy about this,
不過他們覺得我們讓雷曼退出是對的
but they like that we let Lehman go.
你態度強硬 你果敢 在這種時候 人們需要的就是這種態度
You stood strong. You've got brass balls. It's what people need at a time like this.
市場反應怎麼樣?
What is the market doing?
歐洲股指只出現小幅下跌 道瓊斯指數也小幅下探了3%
Europe's only down a little. Dow Jones futures only off 3 %.
那你就得在新聞發佈會上強調這點
So you need to build on this at the press conference.
你要告訴大家我們已經為雷曼兄弟做了我們能做的一切
The story is we did everything we could for Lehman.
- 我們的確做了  - 但是放棄的理由是...
- We did.  - And the takeaway is...
沒有援助資金了
No more bailouts.
部長先生
Mr. Secretary.
我們應該如何解讀發生在雷曼兄弟身上的事件?
How should we read what happened with Lehman?
解讀成我認為維護市場的穩定和金融系統的有序
Read it as I think it's important to maintain the stability
是至關重要的
and orderliness of our financial system,
還有 呃 就是
and, um, the
我非常重視道德風險
moral hazard is something I don't take lightly.
- Paulson先生  - 部長 先生
- Mr. Paulson.  - Mr. Secretary, sir.
你認為現在的銀行體系是否健全?
How do you see the health of the banking system today?
當今市場的運行
The way the markets are performing today,
是對於驗證在極端情況下
it's a testament to how the financial industry has come together
整個金融行業是否能同心協力渡過難關的考驗
in an extraordinary set of circumstances.
美國民眾應該對金融系統的穩健和韌性
The American people can remain confident in the soundness and the resilience
持樂觀態度 謝謝各位
of the financial system. Thank you all.
- 部長大人  - Paulson先生
- Mr. Secretary.  - Mr. Paulson.
怎麼了?
What?
道瓊斯大幅下挫 已經下跌了400點了
Dow is falling off a cliff. Four hundred points already.
整個信貸市場也處於凍結狀態
And the credit markets are frozen.
高盛和摩根斯坦利收到大量撤資申請
Goldman and Morgan Stanley are getting slammed by withdrawals.
雷曼事件正在危及他們
The Lehman thing's killing them.
我得和總統談談我們該如何控制損失
I should talk to the President about how we'll contain the damage.
在你找總統談話之前
Before you speak to the President,
我們還有個麻煩需要解決
we've got another problem.
是美國國際集團
AIG.
Geithner先生正在同美國國際集團探討由企業主導的解決方案
Mr. Geithner is working with AIG on a private-sector solution
部長正非常謹慎地跟進他們的進展
and the Secretary is monitoring their progress very carefully.
他與國會領導者們也保持密切聯繫...
He's in close contact with the Congressional leadership, most...
白宮希望我們對美國國際集團的情況做簡要匯報
White House wants a briefing on AIG.
你知道的比我們多 我們有的信息 你也有
You're more informed about that than we are. We've got the same information you do.
不 我們並不認為雷曼兄弟破產
No, we don't believe that Lehman's bankruptcy
足以整垮整個華爾街
is taking down all of Wall Street.
好吧 那你怎麼解釋...
Okay, but how do you explain...
美國國際集團的情況惡化的原因在於...
The AIG situation may have been, you know, exacerbated by the...
還有Barney Frank的辦公室
And Barney Frank's office.
- 你好  - 突然發生?
- Yeah.  - A surprise?
不 美國國際集團已經掙扎了...
No, AIG has been struggling...
你們這幫人怎麼沒在6個月前阻止他們?
Why didn't you guys head off this situation six months ago?
因為我們沒有魔杖 Doug
Because the requisite magic wand wasn't available, Doug.
如果我們找到了 我們會在第一時間通知你
But if we do find one, you will be among the very first to know.
Blankfei在四號線 緊急
Blankfein on four, urgent.
我得走了
I have to go.
嗨 Lloyd
Hey, Lloyd.
這該死的英國破產管理人
The goddamn British bankruptcy administrator
把所有雷曼客戶的資產都凍結了
froze all of Lehman's customer accounts.
在你下決定之前你沒有和他們協商好嗎?
You didn't square this with the British before you did it?
Geithner 5號線
Geithner on five.
人們陷入了恐慌 他們拿不到錢
People are freaking out. They can't get their money.
不是投資者們 是客戶們
Not investors, clients.
如果消費者覺得他們的錢放在雷曼那兒不安全
If customers think their money wasn't safe with Lehman,
他們也不會相信我們
they're not gonna trust us either.
沒人願意和我們做生意
No one will do business with us.
你得等我一下
You're gonna have to hang on.
Tim啊
Tim.
Dan和穆迪投資評級機構通話了 他們今晚要下調對美國國際集團的評級
Dan spoke to Moody's. They're downgrading AIG tonight.
雖說這事兒遲早會發生 但雷曼事件加速了下調的進程
Would have happened anyway, but Lehman put the whole thing into hyperdrive.
會降到哪一級?
How far down are they?
法國財政部長 6號線
French Finance Minister on six.
他們不知道
They don't know.
我們在努力挽救
We're working on it.
Christine啊
Christine.
你怎麼能讓這事情發生在雷曼身上?
How could you let this happen with Lehman?
Christine Lagarde 法國財政部長
你到底怎麼想的?
What on earth were you thinking?
我們已做了我們該做的一切 Christine
We did everything we could, Christine.
你默許了雷曼破產 Hank 這大錯特錯
You allowed it to fail, Hank. It was a horrifying mistake.
這會給整個歐洲帶來災難性的結果
It is having catastrophic consequences all over Europe.
美國國際集團的情況會變得更糟
And AIG would be even worse.
整個歐洲銀行都與美國國際集團往來密切
The European banks have tremendous exposure to AIG.
我們希望從你這兒得到保證 你不會讓它像雷曼一樣破產
We need assurance you will not fail to act, as you did with Lehman.
這不僅僅是美國的問題
It is not just an American problem.
非常感謝...
Thank you so much for...
是John Mack
John Mack.
- John  - John 一號線
- John.  - John, one.
雷曼的破產正連累著我們
The fallout from Lehman is killing us.
做空者都在拋售我們的股票 我們已經跌了10%
The short-sellers are all over us. We're down 10 % already.
你們不知道外面情況有多糟
You guys have no idea what's going on out here.
你的收入怎麼樣?
How are your earnings?
很好 我們準備週五公佈消息
Strong. We're gonna announce Friday.
現在就公佈
Announce now.
好了 Lloyd 不好意思
Okay, Lloyd, sorry.
Hank 如果儲戶們發現他們不能從雷曼的賬戶上取款
Hank, if depositors see they can't get their assets out of Lehman,
接下來就會有大批人從各投資銀行撤資
the next step is gonna be a massive pullout from all the investment banks.
Jeff Immelt 通用電氣
Jeff Immelt from GE.
天吶 Immelt為什麼打電話給你?
Jesus, what's Immelt calling you for?
我得掛了 Jeff
I have to go. Jeff.
你得知道現在時態變成什麼樣子
You gotta know what's going on out here.
Jeffery Immelt 世界最大公司 通用電氣 主席兼首席執行官
我們每天的營運現金流出現了問題
We're having trouble funding our day-to-day operations.
我們的財務部影響其他各個部門
Our finance division is infecting the rest of our business.
通用電氣?
General Electric?
這件事情波及的不僅僅是華爾街的公司
This thing is spreading way past Wall Street.
我明白沒有人想去碰次級貸款
I get that nobody wants to touch mortgages,
但我們要製造飛機 引擎 燈泡
but we're making planes and engines, light bulbs.
我們是家健康的企業
We're a healthy company.
如果我們不能有充足的日常營運資金來運營公司
If we can't finance our day-to-day operations,
那我們在美國所有的業務都有可能無法運作
every business in America's gonna be shutting down.
- 美國國際集團股價多少?  - 收盤價2美元
- Where's AIG?  - It closed at $2.
Tim覺得我們得採取有力行動 Ben和我都同意了
Tim thinks we need to do something big. Ben agrees, and so do I.
我們能做什麼? 美國國際集團又不是銀行
What can we do? AIG's not even a bank.
聯邦政府會在非常緊急時期借錢給非銀行機構
The Fed can lend to non-banks under unusual and exigent circumstances.
我們考慮接手80%美國國際集團的股份
We're thinking of taking over 80% of the company.
Hank 我們不能這麼做
Hank, we can't.
今天上午我們還向全體公民普及了道德風險觀念
This morning we were lecturing the entire country on moral hazard.
美國國際集團有抵押品 他們有資產
AIG has collateral. They have assets.
雷曼兄弟沒有 我們不能借錢給一個無底洞
Lehman didn't. We couldn't lend into a hole.
兩者情況不同
It's not the same story.
沒人會在乎這些
Nobody's gonna care.
這又是一樁沒有監管的注資行為
It's another bailout with no legislation.
國會會大做文章 整個國家也會抓狂的
The Hill's gonna go crazy. The country's gonna go crazy.
我們早上乘坐的班機是從美國國際集團租賃的
The plane that we flew in on this morning, leased from AIG.
在市中心的建設 是美國國際集團承接的
Construction downtown, AIG.
壽險 8100萬份保單 賬面價值1.9兆億元
Life insurance, 81 million policies with a face value of 1.9 trillion,
上百億的教師退休金 美國國際集團的資產到處都是
billions of dollars in teachers' pensions, it's everywhere.
你想要大而不倒? 就是這個了
You want too big to fail? Here it is.
你有更好的主意嗎? 我可是聽著呢
You got a better idea? The suggestion box is wide open.
我也知道現在說這個不太恰當
I hate to do this right now,
但我得明天一大早得召開新聞發佈會
but I'm gonna have to have a press call first thing,
但我真不知道該對他們說什麼
and I really don't know what I'm gonna tell them.
告訴他們雷曼拖累了美國國際集團 同時兌現債務抵押債券
Tell them Lehman exacerbated AIG. The simultaneous payouts of CDOs
和信用違約掉期幾乎要壓垮...
and credit default swaps put catastrophic pressure on...
再往前追述一點
Go back further.
全球的投資的資金池...
The global pool of investment capital...
她得用英文來發佈 從房地產業主開始說起
She has to do this in English. Start with the homeowners.
好吧 好吧 你該這麼解釋
Okay, okay, here's how you explain it.
華爾街開始將房產抵押貸款捆綁 形成住房抵押貸款證券
Wall Street started bundling home loans together, mortgage-backed securities,
再分成一份一份賣給投資者
and selling slices of those bundles to investors.
他們借此謀取暴利
And they were making big money,
於是他們就開始催促放貸者 說道
so they started pushing the lenders, saying,
"快點 我們需要更多的貸款"
"Come on, we need more loans."
放貸者已經將把錢放給信用等級高的借款人
The lenders had already given loans to borrowers with good credit,
於是他們退而求其次 降低標準
so they go bottom-feeding. They lower their criteria.
以前你需要有620積分的信用評分 加上20%的首付
Before, you needed a credit score of 620 and a down payment of 20%.
現在 500就可以了 零首付
Now, they'll settle for 500, no money down.
至於買方 走在大街上的普通人
And the buyer, the regular guy on the street,
以為專家們知道他們在幹什麼
assumes that the experts know what they're doing.
他自言自語道 "如果銀行願意借我錢
He's saying to himself, "If the bank's willing to loan me money,
"那我肯定還得起"
"I must be able to afford it."
所以他開始實現自己的美國夢
So he reaches for the American dream.
他買下了房子
He buys that house.
銀行知道債券掛鉤垃圾貸款是非常危險的
The banks knew securities based on shitbag mortgages were risky.
你得強調 "垃圾"這個詞
You'll work on "shitbag."
為了控制負面影響 銀行會開始購買一種保險
So to control their downside, the banks started buying a kind of insurance.
如果抵押貸款違約 保險公司買單
If mortgages default, insurance company pays,
違約掉期
default swap.
銀行為他們的潛在損失投保 使報表中不會出現風險
The banks insure their potential losses to move the risk off their books
這樣他們可以進行更多的投資 賺更多的錢
so they can invest more, make more money.
如果很多公司投保
And while a lot of companies insured this stuff,
那麼就有一家公司蠢得要承擔難以置信的風險
one was dumb enough to take on an almost unbelievable amount of risk.
- 美國國際集團  - 你要強調"蠢"
- AIG.  - And you'll work on "dumb."
那如果他們問我為什麼他們會這麼做呢?
And when they ask me why they did that?
- 手續費  - 上億的手續費
- Fees.  - Hundreds of millions in fees.
美國國際集團估計房地產市場會繼續走高
AIG figured the housing market would just keep going up,
可是意外發生了
but then the unexpected happens.
房價下跌
Housing prices go down.
這窮光蛋買了他的夢想之屋
The poor bastard who bought his dream house,
這惱人的抵押貸款利率不停上升
the teaser rate on his mortgage runs out.
他的還款額上升 他違約了
His payments go up. He defaults.
次級抵押證券出了問題 美國國際集團必須償還掉期
Mortgage-backed securities tank. AIG has to pay off the swaps,
全球 同一時間 所有的保單違約了
all of them, all over the world, at the same time.
美國國際集團付不起了 入不敷出
AIG can't pay. AIG goes under.
每一家他們承保的銀行都在同一天要求兌現保費
Every bank they insure books massive losses on the same day.
他們都入不敷出了
And then they all go under.
都倒閉了
It all comes down.
整個金融系統?
The whole financial system?
那我該怎麼說 如果他們問我為什麼這件事情沒有得到妥善監管?
And what do I say when they ask me why it wasn't regulated?
沒人想去監管
No one wanted to.
經濟形勢表現得太好了
We were making too much money.
你得強調 "經濟形勢表現得太好了"
You'll work on "We were making too much money."
喂 Hank 呃...
Hey, Hank. Um...
這些很溫和 不過很有效
These are really mild, but they work.
我知道你信基督教科學派 不吃藥(該派認為物質是虛幻的 疾病只能靠調整精神來治療)
I know the whole Christian Scientist thing, that you don't take medicine.
不過你需要睡眠
But you need to sleep.
- Jim...  - Hank 不僅僅是為了你自己 好嗎?
- Jim...  - Hank, not just for your own sake. Okay?
你看起來不太好
You don't look so good.
就在幾分鐘前 CNN得到確切消息 美聯儲正在協調
Just minutes ago, CNN has confirmed that the Federal Reserve is negotiating
拯救保險巨頭美國國際集團
to rescue insurance giant AIG.
協調計劃包括一份850億美金的臨時貸款
The negotiations could include an $85 billion temporary loan
用以延緩美國國際集團面臨的倒閉
to stave off AIG's imminent collapse.
朋友們 這可是個爆炸新聞
This is a blockbuster, folks.
差不多昨天的這時候 很多在華爾街的人
About this time last night, many on Wall Street
擔心今天會是一團亂
were fearing total disaster today.
於是 聯邦政府又一次注資拯救另一家華爾街巨頭
So, another federal bailout of another Wall Street giant.
還有 我們提到的 是一起重大的 重大的金融消息
Again, as we mentioned, big, big financial news.
並且這條消息影響到每一個買過401k養老保險計劃的人
And this affects almost everyone out there who has a 401k.
這條消息在股市收市的三個半小時後發佈出來...
The news comes about three and a half hours after the stock exchange closed on...
哦上帝啊
Motherfucker.
我們現在馬上把時間交給Ali Velshi來看看這次危機的底線在哪 Ali
We wanna go straight right now to Ali Velshi to kind of give us a bottom line on this, Ali.
然後我們來看看這次危機是不是會持續下去...
And then we're gonna get a lot more in depth...
美國國際集團得到了收於850億的救援...
AIG securing an 85...
信貸市場的資金流動依舊很少
The credit markets are still frozen solid.
如果我們繼續想這些公司注資
We keep dumping money into these companies
那麼市場會慢慢穩定下來
so the markets will stabilize,
除此之外沒別的辦法了
and nothing helps.
我們不能一直這樣
We can't keep doing this.
我們無條件的救了貝爾斯登 又無條件的救了美國國際集團
We rescued Bear with no legislation, AIG with no legislation.
人們會認為房利美和房地美在誘售
People think Fannie and Freddie was a bait-and-switch.
你以為我願意這樣做嗎 但是他們的狀況都很特殊
I don't like it any more than you do, but they were exceptional situations.
現在的情況要求
This situation demands an endgame
那些公司不能再依靠聯邦政府的協助
that does not rely on unilateral action from the Fed.
這才是民主
This is a democracy.
我們不能垂簾聽政在幕後操縱
We cannot be men behind the curtain pulling the strings.
我們需要找到一個完善的解決方法來修復整個金融體系
We need some kind of an overall solution that heals the entire system.
並且是通過合法的方式進行
And it has to be legitimate.
我們一再推遲了向國會匯報這些事情
We've been putting off going to Congress.
離大選只有兩個月了
It's two months before an election.
選民們不可能投票給一個使得整個銀行系統崩潰的政府
They can't vote yes to a massive bailout of the entire banking system.
- 選民們不可能再選擇我們  - Hank...
- They'd never get reelected.  - Hank...
我們去國會說清楚我們已經對現在的局勢
We go to Congress, publically state we don't have the firepower
無能為力了 但是他們說不行
to control this anymore, and then they say no,
這種場景真是一場噩夢
that is really the nightmare scenario.
噩夢場景已經出現了 我的朋友
The nightmare scenario's already here, my friend.
而且我們深陷其中
We're in it.
P你還好嗎
P.
你不能把所有事情都自己扛下來
You can't put this all on your own shoulders.
我們已經別無選擇了
We're running out of options.
那麼你就繼續嘗試別的方法 這才是你該做的
Then you just keep trying. That's what you do.
最後肯定會有辦法解決的
Eventually something's gonna work.
我都不知道 是不是這樣的了
I'm not sure that that is true anymore.
但是這世界上沒有一家銀行是有足夠的錢去應對
There's not a bank in the world that has enough money in its vault
儲戶的提款要求 銀行都是建立在信用基礎上的
to pay its depositors. It's all built on trust.
而且 Wendy 我們已經岌岌可危了
And, Wendy, we are so very close.
摩根斯坦利 高盛已經在懸崖邊緣
Morgan Stanley, Goldman are an inch away.
如果別的銀行不再信任他們 如果他們停止了銀行間的拆借
If the other banks stop trusting them, if they pull back on interbank lending,
他們會立刻破產
it's over in a matter of hours.
而且一旦破產開始了就不會停下來 會有連鎖反應
And from there it goes too fast to stop, a run,
而且到時候破產的就不僅僅是銀行了 整個金融系統都會崩塌
and not just on one bank, I mean on the whole system.
然後大眾就會問 "我的錢安全嗎?"
And average people wondering, "Is my money safe?"
他們開始提現
They start pulling their cash.
再然後 銀行門口就會排起長隊 ATM機就會被擠爆
And after that, lines outside the banks, smashed ATMs.
再過幾個星期
A couple of weeks,
銀行奡N沒有錢可以提了
there's no milk in the store.
這已經是本周第二次
For the second time this week,
華爾街出現了大量的拋售
there was a massive sell-off on Wall Street,
道瓊斯工業指數暴跌超過450點
the Dow Jones Industrial's freefalling some 450 points
因為消息稱納稅人的資金用來救援美國國際集團保險公司
on news of a taxpayer-funded bailout of the AIG insurance company.
五大投行中三家已經倒閉了
Three of the five investment banks are gone.
全國最大的抵押貸款機構也倒閉了
The country's biggest mortgage lender is gone.
房利美 房地美也已經收歸國有
Fannie Mae, Freddie Mac, brought under government control.
金融系統現在算是保住了 但是能維持多久?
The financial system is holding right now, but for how long?
全部人力 全部資源都被完全利用
All the king's horses and all the king's men
一定保持金融體系的順利運行
are being brought to bear to keep this thing together.
- 嗨 Tim  - 我在華爾街 Hank
- Hi, Tim.  - I'm on the Street, Hank,
人們正要趕著去上班
and people are just going about their business.
他們完全不知道這堛漱@切都將化為烏有
They have no idea the whole thing is about to fall down.
我們不得不向國會報告了 我們已經別無選擇
We're gonna have to go to Congress. We don't have a choice anymore.
好吧
Okay.
你覺得還要多久他們會做出決定?
How fast do you think you can get them to move?
我想至少也要幾天
It's gonna be at least a couple days.
高盛和摩根斯坦利已經快不行了
Goldman and Morgan Stanley are going down now.
我們今天必須做點什麼
We gotta do something today.
比如說?
Like what?
市場不像投行一樣 對嗎?
The market doesn't like investment banks, right?
所有的商業模型都拿那些錢束手無策
The money's saying "fuck you" to the whole business model.
是的
Yeah.
是的 那讓他們變成商業銀行
Yeah, so merge them with commercial banks,
把投行變成普通的由聯邦政府監管的商業銀行
turn them into regular banks regulated by the Fed.
他們就能動用儲戶的錢了
They can use depositors' cash.
這樣他們就能通過貼現窗口
It will give them access to the discount window.
向政府以較低的利率借款
It's cheap government cash.
- 你想讓他們變得更大嗎?  - 這也是沒辦法的辦法 Hank
- You wanna make them bigger?  - It's a trade-off, Hank.
好處是他們可以逐漸穩定下來
The upside is it'll stabilize them.
壞處是
The downside is,
對的 他們會變得出奇的龐大
yeah, they'll be really fucking big.
去做吧 Tim
Do it, Tim.
快去做
Godspeed.
嗯 給我接Blankfein
Uh, get me Blankfein.
Lloyd 打電話給Vikram Pandit 告訴他你想合併
Lloyd, call Vikram Pandit, talk to him about a merger.
Tim 我們正在盡全力想辦法
Tim, we're looking at all our options.
你已經走投無路了 Lloyd 你的銀行只能這樣做
You don't have options, Lloyd. There's a run on your bank.
你需要錢 花旗又有存款
You need money. Citi has deposits.
花旗現在一團糟 你這埵陰齯ㄞ 打電話給Pandit
Citi's a mess, you're organized. Call Pandit.
怎麼了
Yeah.
我希望你可以考慮考慮和摩根斯坦利合併
I want you to look at merging with Morgan Stanley.
什麼 你在開玩笑吧? 我剛剛買了貝爾斯登
What, are you kidding me? I just bought Bear.
我們仍然在想辦法讓它開始好轉
We're still trying to make that work.
你沒有買貝爾斯登 它幾乎算是送你的
You didn't buy Bear. You got Bear as a Christmas present.
市場現在一團糟 Jamie 跟John Mack聊聊
The market's a fucking disaster, Jamie. Talk to John Mack.
嘿 Geithner說我們可以談談合併的事情
Hey, Geithner says we should talk about a merger.
- 你想這樣做嗎?  - 當然不想
- You wanna do a deal?  - No.
那他為什麼要讓我打給你?
Then why the fuck did he tell me to call you?
我得到命令去幫助你們公司
I'm under orders to try and help you.
你是個王子 Jamie 真的是王子
You're a prince, Jamie. A real prince.
很顯然 有人認為把我們的公司進行合併是一個不錯的方法
Apparently, some people seem to think combining our firms would be a good idea.
我想說我對於這通電話受寵若驚
I want you to know I'm flattered by this call.
Vikram 我沒有奉承你的意思 相信我
Vikram, I'm not trying to flatter you, believe me.
Geithener打電話來了
Geithner's calling.
一攤子破事
Here comes goddamn eHarmony.
嘿 猜猜看 Jamie一點都不感興趣
Hey, guess what. Jamie's not interested.
試試Wachovia
Do Wachovia.
他們是閉著眼睛進行抵押貸款買賣的
They were writing mortgages with their eyes closed.
Tim 那只是一塊垃圾三明治 忘了他吧
Tim, it's a shit sandwich. Forget it.
我在四小時之內是趕不到你那邊的
I haven't been able to reach you for four hours.
這在今天這樣的日子堛眯w是做不到的
That is totally fucking unacceptable on a day like today.
我不得不讓我的公司去評估高盛合併事宜
I had to run my team through the Goldman proposal.
沒用的
It's not gonna work.
你已經聯繫好高盛了 卻沒給我說一聲?
You passed on Goldman without even talking to me?
我不需要在我的資產負債表上多出1兆億的美元
I don't need another trillion dollars on my balance sheet.
下次我打給你的時候 記得接電話
Next time I call, pick up.
去死吧
Fucker.
問題就在於那些不良資產 我們把他們買過來就好了
The problem is the toxic assets. Let's just buy them.
哦 可以稱為現金換垃圾
Ooh. We'll call it Cash for Trash.
當市場穩定下來了 我們再把這些垃圾傾銷掉
When the market stabilizes, we'll unload them.
希望是這樣 財政部能夠把這些錢討回來
Hopefully, Treasury will get its money back.
- 這是破杯計劃的一部分嗎?  - 基本上是
- Is that in the Break the Glass plan?  - Basically.
我的這份是不是少了幾頁 有誰能告訴我餘下的幾頁...
My copy's missing some pages. Could someone else show me the rest of...
這個是簡潔版
It's succinct.
我們在國會只有一次機會
We've got one shot with Congress.
你覺得國會會根據這三頁紙就簽署一份法案嗎?
You want them to write a piece of legislation based on three pages?
聽著 朋友們
Look, guys,
購買不良資產肯定是一個噩夢
buying toxic assets is gonna be a nightmare.
沒人知道這些東西到底值幾個子
Nobody knows what the stuff's worth.
也許這些不良資產永遠都理不清 銀行馬上就要倒閉了
It'll take forever to untangle. These banks are going down now.
那我們能怎麼做?
So what do we do?
你想要讓信用市場繼續運作 是嗎? 你希望銀行能夠繼續放貸?
You wanna unfreeze credit, right? You want the banks to lend people money?
- 這就是我們想要看到的  - 那就給他們錢讓他們放貸
- That's the goal.  - So give them money to lend.
資產注入?
Capital injections?
Dan 擺脫別說傻話
Dan, come on.
我不相信你竟然說出了那個帶 "N" 的字眼
I can't believe you're pulling out the "N" word.
我沒有說要將銀行國有化
I'm not saying nationalize the banks.
我說的是把有問題的銀行隔離開 然後進行注資
I'm saying isolate the ones that are really in trouble and make an investment.
- 這做法不是美國人做的  - 當然也不是共和黨人做的
- It's un-American.  - It's sure un-Republican.
你讓政府變成了一個股東
You'd make the government a stockholder.
什麼 我們是不是需要告訴他們怎麼去經營 買哪些賣哪些?
What, do we tell them how to manage themselves, what to buy and sell?
像經營郵局一樣經營他們? 是那樣就太好了
Run them like the post office? 'Cause that works like a dream.
這只是暫時措施 我們可以是沒有投票權的股東
We make it temporary. We make ourselves non-voting stockholders.
你不能捧著一疊疊的鈔票送到銀行
You can't just hand the banks massive piles of cash.
沒人會去理會這些的
Nobody's gonna go for it.
對於共和黨來說這是資產國有化 對於民主黨來說這就是救助
To the Republicans it's nationalization. To the Democrats it's a bailout.
而且銀行會很生氣的
And the banks are gonna go ballistic.
抱歉 Dan 這是不可能的 很欣賞你的創造性思維
Sorry, Dan, not gonna happen. Kudos for out-of-the-box thinking.
Neel 如果我們實行你的計劃購買那些資產
Neel, if we go with your plan to buy the assets,
我們會花多少錢?
how much is it gonna cost?
那是不可能的
It won't work.
聽著 計劃只有3頁長 而且很空洞
Look, the plan is three pages long, totally vague.
如果購買資產沒有用的話 我們會用你的國有化計劃 好嗎?
If buying the assets doesn't work, we'll nationalize the banks for you, okay?
- 要多少錢?  - 保守估計 需要一萬億
- How much? - To be safe, maybe a trillion.
國會是不會批准一萬億的法案的 永遠不會
The Congress will never do a trillion, never.
有11萬億美元的住房抵押債券
There's $11 trillion in residential mortgages.
還有三萬億的商業債券 一共是十四萬億 對嗎?
There's three trillion in commercial mortgages. That's 14 trillion, right?
別忘了5%的違約率
You gotta figure about 5% default rate.
14萬億的5%是
5 % of 14 trillion is
七千萬美元
$700 billion.
這也比一萬億要好
It's better than a trillion.
讓法案通過的唯一方法只能是嚇得他們屁滾尿流
The only way to get this done is to just scare them shitless.
這很簡單 我自己都嚇傻了
That should be easy. I'm scared shitless myself.
2008年9月18日 星期四 雷曼兄弟破產後三天
Barney Frank(馬薩諸塞州代表) 眾議院金融管理委員會主席
問題資產剝離計劃?
Troubled Asset Relief Program?
我們稱他為TARP
TARP, we're calling it.
這只是你們的草案?
This is your draft of the bill?
這只是一個修訂本 肯定的
Subject to revision, certainly.
Chris Dodd(康乃迪克州代表) 參議院銀行委員會主席
我只拿到了三頁紙 我是不是漏掉了什麼?
I've only got three pages here. Am I missing something?
沒有
No.
Richard Shelby(阿拉巴馬州代表) 參議院銀行委員會副主席
你在著急尋找的只是一張大額的空白支票
You're just looking for a big blank check in a hurry.
這都是為了銀行 你也不想
It's all for the banks. You don't want a penny
讓布什總統失去他的總統位置
for the average Joe that's about to lose his house?
整件事完全沒有任何監管
There's not a scrap of oversight built into this,
錢沒有給銀行 也沒有給你 只是為了解決這個情況
not for the banks or for you, for that matter.
你希望我們簡簡單單的拿出7000萬來相信你?
You want us to simply hand over $700 billion and trust you?
Nancy Pelosi(加利福尼亞州代表) 眾議院發言人
你怎麼可能沒有想到我們的反應?
How is it possible you didn't see this coming?
如果你們想讓我再說一遍的話 我沒有問題
If you wanna rewind the tape, we can do that.
但是現在 最重要的是我們沒時間了
But right now, the one thing we don't have is time.
我們今晚需要一個決議來穩定市場
We need an announcement tonight to calm the market.
我們需要法案在下周通過
We need legislation next week.
我學術研究的內容只有一個
I spent my entire academic career
就是大蕭條
studying the Great Depression.
大蕭條的起因是因為股票市場的崩盤
The Depression may have started because of a stock market crash,
但是打擊到實體經濟的是信用體系的瓦解
but what hit the general economy was a disruption of credit,
普通群眾無法借錢去做任何事 沒法賣房子
average citizens unable to borrow money to do anything, to buy a home,
沒法做生意 沒法進貨
start a business, stock their shelves.
信用是建立現在經濟的基礎
Credit has the ability to build a modern economy,
但是信用缺乏也可以毀掉經濟 迅雷不及掩耳的毀滅
but lack of credit has the power to destroy it, swiftly and absolutely.
如果我們不能做出明確的決斷 我們將會重演上世紀30年代的大蕭條
If we do not act boldly and immediately, we will replay the Depression of the 1930s,
只是這次情況會更糟 更糟
only this time it will be far, far worse.
如果我們現在不做這些 我們的經濟在週一就完了
We don't do this now, we won't have an economy on Monday.
Geithner的電話
Geithner.
我們把議案交到國會了
We took the proposal down to Congress.
他們會通過嗎?
Are they gonna go for it?
他們不喜歡那麼短的議案
They didn't like the fact that it was short.
我想簡單明瞭可以加分的
I thought concise was a plus.
他們覺得這樣太輕薄或者太傲慢或者別的什麼
They thought it was flimsy or arrogant or something.
我不知道他們怎麼想 但是他們不會通過的
I don't know what they think. They couldn't get past it.
市場已經無法控制了 他們否決這份議案
The market's in a death spiral. They're gonna sink the bill
因為這份議案太短了?
because the proposal is too fucking short?
他們正在研究 他們會把他弄得長一點
They're working on it. They're gonna make it longer,
加入一些其他東西
among other things.
好吧 告訴我你已經有進展了
Look, just tell me you got something.
不 不 我一點進展也沒有
No. No, we're nowhere.
還有誰可以幫助摩根斯坦利?
Who's left for Morgan Stanley?
中國投資有限公司
China Investment Corporation.
嗯 或者是三菱集團
Uh, maybe Mitsubishi.
不 日本人是不會做這筆生意的
No, the Japanese will never do this deal.
那高盛有什麼進展?
How about Goldman?
高盛找到了聯銀行 但是他們被拒絕了
Goldman's looking at Wachovia, but they're so fucked,
就連John Mack都不屑一顧
even John Mack turned up his nose.
你必須讓議案通過
You gotta get that bill passed.
- 我在努力了  - 那就再努力一點 拜託了
- I'm pushing.  - Well, push harder. Please.
這不會有用的 Hank
This isn't working, Hank.
Hank 怎麼了?
Hank?
能讓我單獨待一會兒嗎?
Could you excuse me a moment?
2008年9月21日 雷曼兄弟破產後第六天
哦 我的上帝呀 高先生 高先生
Oh, my God. Gao, Gao.
對於這件事我很抱歉 但是我們無能為力
I am so sorry about this. There's nothing we can do.
這堿O紐約 你知道 我們很高興我們還能在揚基體育館買一杯啤酒
It's New York, you know. We're lucky we can still buy a beer at Yankee Stadium.
別擔心 反正我遲早都會退出的
Don't worry about it. I should quit anyway.
當你準備好了 我們就進去
When you're ready, we'll be inside.
有什麼進展嗎?
Is there any movement there?
他們給了一個低的離譜的價格 我假裝我沒聽見
They made an extremely low opening offer. I pretended I didn't hear it.
如果摩根斯坦利的問題沒有解決 那市場就不能在週一開市
The markets can't open Monday without a resolution of Morgan Stanley.
我們真的很需要你做一個決定
We really need you to do a deal.
- 你打電話給Jamie  - 我打過Jamie了
- You need to call Jamie.  - I called Jamie.
他對我們沒興趣 難度太大了
He doesn't want us. There's too much overlap.
我們已經跟他說過了 他會同意的
We've spoken to him. He'll do it.
為了什麼 為了美元? 我為什麼要這麼做?
For what, a dollar? Why would I do that?
我這媮晹酗之諰M三菱集團求著要我呢
I got China Investment and Mitsubishi kicking my tires.
我知道這些傢伙 他們不可能及時作出決定的
I know those guys. They're not gonna close a deal in time.
我們希望你打電話給Jamie
We want you to call Jamie.
讓我問你個問題
Let me ask you a question.
因為美國國際集團 雷曼和貝爾斯登的事情 已經有3萬5千人失業了
35,000 jobs just disappeared in this city between AIG, Lehman and Bear.
如果我們跟Jamie達成協議 他會裁掉2萬名摩根斯坦利員工
We make a deal with Jamie, he'll fire 20,000 Morgan Stanley employees.
你覺得這是一個好辦法嗎?
You think that's good public policy?
John 我們關注的是整個金融體系的安全
John, we are looking at the whole system here.
中國人走了
The Chinese are leaving.
高先生發現我們還在與三菱集團談判
Gao found out we're also talking to Mitsubishi.
我要走了
I gotta go.
好的 把黑柳找來 再找一個日語翻譯
All right, get me Kuroyanagi and a Japanese translator.
今晚 我們跟三菱要簽好約
We're closing with Mitsubishi tonight.
Tim Geithner又打電話來了
Tim Geithner's calling again.
你就當沒聽見
Cover your ears.
你告訴T?im Geithner別來煩我了 我在想辦法拯救我的公司
You tell Tim Geithner to fucking blow me. I'm trying to save my company.
2008年9月22日 雷曼兄弟破產後7天
我要和他見面 但是確保約在在午飯之後
Put him on the schedule, but make sure it's after lunch,
因為之前我還要與Madeline碰頭 而且...
because that way I can fit Madeline in beforehand. And...
摩根剛才與三菱集團達成交易了
Morgan just made a deal with Mitsubishi.
所以我們是唯一一家沒有援助的銀行了
So we're the only bank with our dick still in the wind.
我再給巴菲特打個電話
I'm calling Buffett again.
爺爺 他們一直在找你 萬一是很重要的事怎麼辦?
Grandpa, they keep calling. What if it's important?
他們總覺得自己很重要
They always think it's important.
好吧 我會快點解決
All right, I'll make it fast.
巴菲特 感謝你回復我 你最近怎麼樣?
Warren, thanks for calling back. How are you?
挺好 Lloyd 這次我能幫你做什麼?
Just fine, Lloyd. What can I do for you today?
我想跟你談談關於入股高盛的事情
I'd like to talk to you about taking a stake in Goldman Sachs.
什麼價位? 聽上去很貴
What do you have in mind? Sounds expensive.
也許不貴
Maybe not.
你最好給我的是好消息
You better have good news,
也許搞定TRAP之前 我就掛了
because I might be dead before we finish haggling over TARP.
巴菲特準備給高盛注資五十億
Buffett's throwing five billion into Goldman.
我們脫離險境
We're off the ledge.
暫時而已
For the moment.
十月的驚喜來的早了點
The October surprise arrived a little early,
白宮的總統競爭出現了轉機
with a game-changing jolt to the White House race.
是該叫做出奇制勝還是孤注一擲
Call it a master stroke or a desperate Hail Mary pass,
麥凱恩宣佈他將暫停競選
McCain announced he would suspend his campaign
並要求推遲星期五的辯論
and asked for this Friday's debate to be postponed
以便他能回到華盛頓集中精力應對金融危機
so he can return to Washington to focus on the economic crisis.
現在是我們團結一致的時機 再次證明華盛頓有能力
Now is our chance to come together to prove that Washington is once again
領導國家
capable of leading this country.
感謝上帝 他回來了
Thank God he came back.
就像大地英豪堛慣aniel Day-Lewis(演員)
Like Daniel Day-Lewis in Last of the Mohicans,
他會拯救我們的!
he will find us!
- 他們要搞砸了  - 發生了什麼?
- They're blowing it up.  - What happened?
麥凱恩想趁機介入 挽救局面 但壓根不知道怎麼下手
McCain wanted to swoop in and save the day, but doesn't have any idea how to do it.
這可是我們認真商量好幾天 寫了100頁的法案
It's a 100-page piece of legislation we've been carefully negotiating for days.
他以為我們就坐著這玩扔紙團?
What, did he think they were gonna sit around and spitball?
是的 當麥凱恩到這
Yeah, when McCain got here
並且發現這事情已經基本解決完了 他就憤怒了
and found out that the deal was basically done, he went apeshit.
共和黨沒跟上進度 他們想重新來一遍
The Republicans fell in behind their guy. They wanna start all over again.
民主黨發飆 共和黨想插進來
Democrats flipped out. Republicans dug in.
- 亂七八糟  - 亂七八糟
- Clusterfuck.  - Clusterfuck.
- Hank在哪? - 還在跟麥凱恩說話
- Where's Hank?  - Still talking to McCain.
如果你或者任何其他人做了任何事
If you or anyone else does anything
導致新一輪的大蕭條 可別賴在我身上
that causes the next depression, it is not gonna be on me.
我嘴巴很不嚴的 參議員
I have a big mouth, Senator,
- 口風很鬆  - 等等
- a very big mouth. - Hold on...
他不是在威脅共和黨總統候選人吧?
He's not threatening the Republican presidential nominee, is he?
- 必須採取一些行動  - 不 不 抱歉 離開一下
- Something's gotta be done.  - No, no. Excuse me, please.
民主黨的人在哪?
Where are the Democrats?
他們就在走廊那頭
They're right down this way.
- Nancy在嗎?  - 是的 她在
- Is Nancy there?  - Yes. Yes, she is.
謝了
Thank you.
Nancy啊...
Nancy...
哦 上帝 Hank 我不知道你還是天主教徒
Oh, Gee, Hank. I didn't know you were Catholic.
我請求你 別毀了這個提案 這次會議很糟糕
I beg of you, don't blow this up. It was a bad meeting,
但是我們必須達成共識
but we need to get together on this.
我們不是想破壞這個提案的一方
We're not the ones trying to blow it up.
我只是請求你能支持我們
I just ask you to stay with us.
拜託了
Please.
參議院在今早9點27分開始討論援助議案
The House began debating the rescue bill at 9:27 this morning.
約在下午1點28分 國會完成最終投票
At about 1:28 p.m., Congress did finally act.
- 票數非常接近  - 我們馬上來看一下
- This is a squeaker of a vote.  - We are down to it right now.
似乎贊成票大多來自民主黨
It looks like the Democrats delivered their caucus
而目前來看共和黨不大贊同此議案
and the Republicans so far have not.
你認為他們會怎樣修改議案
What do you think they could do to change the bill
以便贏得共和黨的選票?
to get a few Republican votes over to the other side?
如果他們吊死那些華爾街的首席執行官
If they hang Wall Street CEOs,
我想他們也許能得到更多的選票
I think that would get a few more votes.
我不清楚他們具體能做些什麼
I'm not sure what they could do exactly.
國會的領導很可能認為
It is possible that the leadership of the Congress would conclude
沒有任何解決方法可以得到多數票的支持
that there's nothing that can get a majority of support
就看Hank Paulson和當局能怎麼做了
and see what Hank Paulson can do and the administration can do.
領導們正在協商
Leaders are negotiating right now
誰會拿自己的職位冒險 這就是我所聽到的
who risks their seat. And that's what I'm hearing.
如果Pelosi覺得議案不能通過的話
Pelosi wouldn't have brought the bill to the floor
就不會將這個議案提上議程
if she didn't think it would pass.
我不知道結果 Charlie 我沒辦法回答
I don't know the answer to that, Charlie. I can't answer.
我正在讀剛收到的一封郵件
I'm just reading an e-mail that's coming to me.
我想最後的底線就是他們還得重新籌劃
I think the bottom line is they gotta go back to the drawing board.
但他們還有時間這麼做嗎?
Do they have the time, though, to do that?
看看道瓊斯工業平均指數
Look at the Dow Jones Industrial Average.
知道嗎 你們將會迎來一個大甩賣
You know you're gonna get a sell-off.
你們 此時此刻 我們只能抓緊救生筏
You guys, at this point, we just gotta hold on to the sides of the kayak
挺過去 因為
and ride through this because...
他們沒通過議案
They didn't pass it.
- 他們沒通過議案  - 這還不夠
- They did not pass it.  - It just wasn't enough.
議案以九票之差 未能獲得通過 Bill
They're gonna end up being nine votes short, Bill.
再說一次 Steve
Say that again, Steve.
我認為他們會以九票之差否決這個議案...
I think they're gonna end up being nine votes...
如果他們得到剩下的六票... 還有五票尚未投出
If they get all six... Five of the remaining votes,
現在他們差10票 剩下的五票都支持議案
they'll be 10 votes short now, if they get all five remaining.
票選結果在牆上
The writing is on the wall there.
我們卻失望的坐在地板上
And we're here down on the floor.
當然 交易員已經站在那
Of course, traders have been standing around.
看著 我們都三五成群的站著...
Look, we're all here in knots...
媒體在新聞發佈室等你
The networks are waiting for you in the press room.
我甚至無法
I can't even...
我們得重頭再來
We have to go back again.
他們不能對新議案說不
They don't get to say no on this.
好的
Okay.
白宮方面想跟你會面
The White House wants a meeting.
很好 我們要帶著新策略去
Good. We'll come up with a new strategy.
白宮必須給國會施壓
The White House has to push harder on the Hill.
同時 我們要想好如何運作資金
Meanwhile, we need to keep working on what we do with the money.
讓我們表現的好像議案能通過一樣
Let's act like this is gonna work.
這種情況下 我們還是談談資本注入吧
In that case, let's talk about cash injections.
- 又來了  - 我們不能把銀行國有化
- Here we go again.  - We can't nationalize the banks.
這不是國有化
It's not nationalizing...
這就是為什麼日本經濟衰退達十年的原因
That's how Japan got itself a decade-long recession.
那就是我們想要的結果嗎?
Is that where we wanna go?
我們還有什麼別的選擇?
What else do we have?
現金換垃圾
Cash for Trash.
購入不良資產依舊是我們的出路
Buying toxic assets is still our go-to move.
好吧 想辦法簡化方案
All right. Find a way to simplify it.
Dan 做個方案出來
Dan, work something up.
讓我們看看會是什麼情況 討論一下
For discussion purposes, let's see what it would look like.
針對那些支持7千億華爾街援助的人而言
For those who supported the $700 billion Wall Street bailout,
這是一次出乎意料的失敗
it was a surprising and stunning failure
當眾議院投票否決此議案時
when the House of Representatives voted to reject it.
對總統布什而言 被共和黨同僚打擊
It's a stinging defeat for President Bush,
是一次慘痛的失敗
delivered at the hands of his fellow Republicans.
我們提出一個宏大的計劃是因為我們面臨著嚴重的問題
We put forth a plan that was big because we've got a big problem.
現實就是我們處在非常緊急的情況下
The reality is that we're in an urgent situation.
並且後果會日益惡化
And the consequences will grow worse each day
如果我們不採取行動
if we do not act.
兩天後
- 我明白 我一直都在說  - 起草新議案
- I know. I keep telling...  - Draft of the new bill.
他們那邊有什麼進展了嗎?
Are they having any luck with it?
白宮認為先向參議院施加壓力
The White House thinks they got a better shot of pushing it
效果會更好 希望他們是對的
through the Senate side first. Hopefully they're right.
他們叫我們收手 交給他們處理
They asked us to back off and let them handle it.
所以我在試著收手
So I'm trying to back off.
購買不良資產還是行不通
Buying toxic assets isn't gonna work.
- 為什麼行不通?  - 太慢了
- Why not?  - It's too slow.
我想我之前就說過
I think I've been saying that.
好吧 我們知道這會很複雜 但是有多慢
Well, we knew it was complicated, but how slow...
兩個月 也許更多
Two months, maybe more.
我們怎麼會不知道...
How is it possible we didn't know how...
我沒問會要多久 行不?
I didn't ask how long it would take, okay?
有別的建議嗎?
Can we move on?
那麼也許我們能談談資本注入
So maybe we can talk about capital injections.
Dan 我們真不能那麼做
Dan, we really can't.
我想我們沒選擇了
I think we're gonna have to.
就算Neel能加快進程 實際上不大可能
Even if Neel could expedite the process, which seems unlikely,
體系正在崩潰 銀行現在就需要錢
the system is crumbling. The banks need money now.
如果注資是穩定整個體系最有效的方式
If cash injections are the most efficient way to stabilize them,
那麼我們就不能
then we can't back off
因為我們不願意成為是要將幾家銀行變成國有化的人而退卻
because we're uncomfortable being the men who nationalized a few American banks.
可以肯定的是 這更快
It's faster, that's for sure.
這能夠把我們從險境中拉出來 是的 激活整個系統
It will push us back off the precipice, yes, unfreeze the system.
我們給他們一些錢然後他們貸出去
We give them some money and they lend it out.
議案通過
The motion is adopted.
在否決布什政府的TARP計劃之後
After rejecting the Bush Administration's TARP plan
僅過了四天 眾議院今日通過了議案
only four days ago, the House passed it today.
現在最大的問題是 投資者是否能從此消息中得到慰藉
The big question now, whether investors will take comfort in the news.
市場指數顯示股票仍在大幅下跌
Current indicators show the stock market is continuing its free fall.
喂?
Hello?
巴菲特 我是Hank
Warren, it's Hank.
抱歉 這麼晚了
I'm sorry. It's late.
我吵醒你了嗎?
Am I waking you?
沒 沒有
No, not at all.
能幫我出出主意嗎?
Can I pick your brain for a minute?
當然 什麼情況?
Sure. What's the problem?
怎麼樣讓一家健全的的銀行接受資本注入?
How do you get a healthy bank to accept a capital injection?
我不得不大老遠從加利福尼亞跑過來
I had to drag my ass all the way here from California.
他們甚至不告訴我為什麼要過來
They wouldn't even tell me why.
沒人知道這是要幹什麼嗎?
Nobody knows what this is about?
不知道
Nope.
跟Jamie談過了?
Talk to Jamie?
恩 他會沒事的
Yep. He'll be fine.
你告訴他接下來要發生什麼了嗎?
Did you tell him what was coming?
額 我告訴他我們會迫使他接受
Uh, did I tell him we're about to make him swallow
不需要的注資了嗎? 沒說
a capital injection he doesn't need? No.
我只告訴他 我們需要他的幫助
I, uh... I told him we need his help
並且我非常禮貌的請求他今天不要跟我們作對
and I asked him very politely not to fuck with us today.
他明白了
He got it.
她在這了
She's here.
Sheila Bair 美國聯邦存款保險公司主席
紳士們 這能奏效嗎?
Gentlemen. We think this is gonna work?
啊 是的 他們會喜歡的
Oh, yeah. They're gonna love it.
我們現在要著眼於美國的實際需求
We are of the view that the United States needs
要採取堅決有力的行動
to take strong, decisive action
以緩解金融體系的壓力
to arrest the stress in our financial system.
通過新授權的TARP方案
Through our new TARP authority,
財政部將向這間房間
Treasury will purchase preferred stock
與會的每家銀行 購買優先股
in each of the banks represented in this room.
頭五年 年收益為5%
That stock will yield 5 % the first five years,
其後為9%
9 % after that.
我們給你錢 你們借出去
We give you money. You lend it out.
這可以激活信貸 穩定銀行 重建信心
It will unfreeze credit, stabilize the banks, restore confidence.
每個人都會因為體系中更多的資金而獲益
Everyone will be better off with more capital in the system.
這就是為什麼你們九個人
And that is why all nine of you
都要參與這個計劃
will participate in the program.
我們中有些人不需要資金
Some of us don't need any capital.
你們都需要
You all need capital.
你們不知道在未來一年堨奕黦|變成什麼樣
You have no idea what the market's gonna look like in a year.
你也不知道
Neither do you.
我可不是你們這些鼓弄新花樣的紐約佬
I'm not one of you New York guys with your fancy products.
為什麼我要呆在這房間堸荈q救助你們?
Why am I in this room talking about bailing you out?
強勢銀行將為弱勢銀行買單
The stronger banks will serve as cover for the weaker banks.
如果只有部分銀行接受注資 那將成為一種信號
If just some of you take it, the money's a signal
就是 這家銀行無法存活 市場將吞噬掉它
that a bank is too weak to survive. The market will devour it.
我們討論的金額是多少?
How much are we talking about?
1250億
A hundred and twenty-five billion.
美國銀行 150億
Bank of America, 15 billion.
紐約梅隆銀行 30億
Bank of New York Mellon, three billion.
花旗集團 250億
Citigroup, 25 billion.
高盛 100億
Goldman Sachs, 10 billion.
摩根大通 250億
JPMorgan, 25 billion.
美林證券 100億
Merrill Lynch, 10 billion.
摩根斯坦利 100億
Morgan Stanley, 10 billion.
道富銀行 20億
State Street, two billion.
富國銀行 250億
Wells Fargo, 25 billion.
購買不良資產的那個方案怎麼了?
What happened to buying toxic assets?
- 那不是個好主意嗎?  - 那樣太慢了
- Wasn't that the idea?  - It's too slow.
在這之前體系就會崩潰
It'll be dead before we sort it out.
所以 我們就這麼把韁繩交給你了?
So, we're just handing the reins over to you?
這筆交易實際上很不錯了
The deal's actually pretty good.
你現在對此不屑一顧 等到我們還是得來援助你的時候
You turn your nose up at this now and we have to rescue you later,
條件可就不這麼有吸引力了
the terms won't be nearly as attractive.
這是很便宜的資本 這不是最差的注意
It's cheap capital. It's not the worst idea in the world.
這是針對我們中間那些已經有足夠資本的
It is for those of us who already have capital.
我們將成為沒投票權的股東 這只是暫時的舉措
We will be non-voting shareholders. This will be a temporary measure.
要是我們拒絕參與呢?
What if we decline to be involved?
美國聯邦存款保險公司的主席就坐在這
The Chairman of the FDIC is sitting right there.
明天你就會發現
Tomorrow you'll find out
你並不像你想的那樣擁有雄厚資本
that you're not as well capitalized as you think you are.
你們會採取什麼樣的保障措施
What kind of protections can you offer on changes
針對補償措施的改變?
for compensation policy?
我的意思是 如果政府要成為共有者
I mean, if the government is going to become a part-owner,
是不是表明將由政府來指定酬金?
does that mean that the government is going to dictate compensation?
此刻你是在問我有關你的獎金問題嗎 John?
Are you asking me about your bonus right now, John?
我在經營一家公司
I'm running a company.
如果美聯儲告訴我 我不能向有才能的人提供有競爭力的薪酬
If the Fed tells me I can't offer competitive pay for talent,
你將導致這個國家有史以來最嚴重的人才流失
you're gonna launch the biggest brain drain this country's ever seen.
這就是你們要經營銀行的方式?
Is that the way you wanna run the banks?
在償還欠款給財政部之前
Until the money is repaid to the Treasury,
會有一些限制扣稅和黃金降落傘(公司控制權變動需要給高管進行補償的協定)的規定
there will be some limitations on tax deductions and golden parachutes.
- 果然  - 我真不明白
- Well, there you go.  - I don't really understand
為什麼討論這個話題還如此嚴肅
why there needs to be so much tension about this.
這個國家在面臨自從大蕭條以來最嚴重的經濟危機
The country is facing the worst economy since the Great Depression.
如果金融體系崩潰 你們每個人都會遭殃
If the financial system collapses, it will take every one of you down.
給我文件
Give me the papers.
- 你不能就這麼簽了  - 哦 為什麼不行?
- You can't just sign it.  - Oh, no?
- 沒有你的董事會的同意  - 我的董事會24小時都待命
- Not without your board. - My board's on 24-hour notice.
我想他們會同意的
I think they'll go along with it.
如果他們不同意 那就炒了我
And if they don't, they'll fire me.
其他人呢?
Anyone else?
他們打算簽嗎?
Are they gonna do it?
他們要聯繫各自的董事會
They're calling their boards.
- 那是個好信號  - 如果他們同意
- That's a good sign.  - If they do go along with this,
我們需要在宣佈注資的同時 公佈其他舉措
we should announce something alongside the injections, uh,
也許是一個收購房屋貸款抵押的計劃
maybe a program to buy up mortgages.
我不想草率的公佈些不成熟的計劃
I'm not rushing out some half-assed plan
只是為了顯示我們做了什麼
just to make it look like we're doing something.
或許我們能補充些限制條件 限制這些錢的用途
Maybe we just beef up the restrictions on how they spend the money,
以去除毒瘤
something to take the stink off.
加更多的條件的話 他們就不會答應了
Put more restrictions on it, they won't take it.
今天完成的事情太多了
One thing too many for today.
我們所知道的是他們差點搞垮了全美國的經濟
They almost bring down the US economy as we know it,
但是我們卻不能限制他們如何使用
but we can't put restrictions on how they spend
我們給他們的1250億美元
the $125 billion we're giving them
就因為他們可能不會接受
because they might not take it.
這是什麼?
What's this?
那是 額
That is, um,
一種有毒鏢蛙
a poison dart frog.
Wendy在圭亞那照的
Wendy took it in Guyana.
這是你的嗎?
Is this yours?
Al Capone(美國黑幫教父)的
Al Capone's.
九家銀行中的八個已經同意了
Eight out of nine are in.
- 美國銀行還在等他的董事會 但是...  - 他也會同意的
- B of A is still waiting on its board, but...  - It's gonna go through.
我要給眾議院辦公室打電話
I'll call the Speaker's office.
還有 我們安排你跟總統電話聯繫下
And, uh, we're gonna get you on the phone with the President.
好的
Okay.
就因為我們的商議 道瓊斯指數漲了900點
Dow is up 900 points just because we were meeting.
太好了
Well, that's good.
That's good.
這樣做是對的
It was the right thing.
絕對的
Absolutely.
我原本準備好應對更強的反對
I was prepared for more blowback.
他們沒有選擇了 他們明白這點
They didn't have a choice. They knew that.
好吧 我當然希望他們
Well, I certainly hope that they...
什麼?
What?
我希望他們會把錢用在我們要求的地方
I hope they use the money the way we're asking them to.
他們會貸出去 是吧?
They will lend it out, won't they?
他們一定會的
Of course they will.
雖然TRAP得到通過 但是幾家銀行仍未進行貸款 市場繼續動盪
失業率超過10% 數百萬的家庭因喪失抵押品贖回權而無家可歸
2009年 動盪的市場逐漸穩定 國際金融形勢的惡化得到緩解
最大的幾家銀行已經贖回了TRAP中政府購買的優先股
2010年 對華爾街的補償已經達到1350億美元的新紀錄
10家銀行的資產占擁有全美銀行資產總數的77%
他們被稱為 大而不倒
--==聖城家園SCG字幕組 http://hd.cnscg.com/==--
僅供翻譯交流使用, 禁止用於商業用途
協調：瀟妹紙
翻譯：Flower一休 千欲 藍岸 wendychen11 13711 Kim
校對：微微